<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine meditations upon some of the virtuous, and vitious women, in the Scriptures wherein, as in a glass, every one may see their own faces; whether fair, or foul; deformed, or comely. A work worthy their spare-hours; which, by the grace of God, may work an holy emulation in many, either to equal, or out-vie their sex in virtue. By William Harvey, minister of the Word of God.</title>
            <author>Harvey, William, minister of the Word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1092B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828184</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32611</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32611)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1948:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine meditations upon some of the virtuous, and vitious women, in the Scriptures wherein, as in a glass, every one may see their own faces; whether fair, or foul; deformed, or comely. A work worthy their spare-hours; which, by the grace of God, may work an holy emulation in many, either to equal, or out-vie their sex in virtue. By William Harvey, minister of the Word of God.</title>
                  <author>Harvey, William, minister of the Word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women in the Bible --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32611:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32611:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DIVINE</hi> MEDITATIONS Upon Some of the <hi>Virtuous,</hi> and <hi>Vitious</hi> WOMEN, in the SCRIPTURES: Wherein, as in a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> every one may ſee their <hi>own Faces;</hi> whether <hi>Fair,</hi> or <hi>Foul; Deformed,</hi> or <hi>Comely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Work</hi> worthy their <hi>Spare-Hours;</hi> which, by the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> may work an <hi>holy Emulation</hi> in many, either to <hi>Equal,</hi> or <hi>Out-vie</hi> their SEX in VIRTUE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM HARVEY, Miniſter</hi> of the WORD of GOD.</p>
            <q>
               <p>A Virtuous Woman is a Crown to her Husband: but ſhe, that maketh aſhamed, is as rotteneſs in his Bones.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xii. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Who can finde a Virtuous Woman? For her price is far above Rubies.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xxxi. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Contraria juxta ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the <hi>Authour,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32611:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32611:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, THE COUNTESS of <hi>South-Hampton,</hi> And the COUNTESS of <hi>North-Hampton, WILLIAM HARVEY</hi> wiſheth all Happineſs in this life, and that, which is to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT <hi>Honourable,</hi> and <hi>Virtuous Ladies,</hi> when I pitched upon this <hi>Subject,</hi> I had You in my <hi>Thoughts:</hi> my <hi>Ambition</hi> was to beg your <hi>Patronage.</hi> As Your <hi>Fortunes,</hi> ſo are Your <hi>Virtues</hi> parallel; and, like the <hi>Gemini</hi> in the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> embrace each other. Your <hi>Titles of Honour</hi> are remote, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, <hi>oppoſite</hi> to other: but, as the
<pb facs="tcp:32611:3"/>
               <hi>needle</hi> in the <hi>Compaſs,</hi> You ever tend to one <hi>ſtar;</hi> and, with the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Daughter,</hi> are both <hi>glorious within.</hi> I ſhall preſent to Your view a <hi>Tragi-Comedy:</hi> the <hi>Actours</hi> be all <hi>Women,</hi> though their <hi>parts</hi> differ. Here You have <hi>Virtue,</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; both brought upon the <hi>Stage</hi> in <hi>lively Colours.</hi> To attract Your attention, the Several <hi>Scenes</hi> are <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred;</hi> for each <hi>Theme</hi> is drawn from <hi>Holy Writ:</hi> an no <hi>Water,</hi> but that, which flows from the <hi>pure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> muſt not expect any <hi>Plot,</hi> or <hi>Aenigmatical paſſages, to puzzle</hi> rather, then <hi>pleaſe</hi> the <hi>Spectatours;</hi> neither look for ſublime, and high <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;</hi> for, the <hi>Subject</hi> being <hi>feminine,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32611:3"/>the matter muſt not <hi>ſpeak big.</hi> Here Your <hi>Ladiſhips</hi> ſhall ſee <hi>plain dealing,</hi> and every woman's <hi>praiſe,</hi> or <hi>diſpraiſe,</hi> as ſhe deſerves. If any one's <hi>mouth</hi> open, they <hi>bark</hi> not at <hi>me;</hi> but <hi>God;</hi> for I have ſpoken nothing, but that, which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> thought fit to <hi>Record.</hi> The <hi>ultimate</hi> end is God's Glory, the next an holy <hi>imitation,</hi> and <hi>detestation</hi> either of <hi>Vice,</hi> or <hi>Virtue.</hi> As <hi>Contraries</hi> put together do <hi>illustrate</hi> each other: So <hi>Sanctitie,</hi> and <hi>Impiete,</hi> oppoſitely placed, will by far, ſeem more <hi>lovely,</hi> or <hi>loathſom.</hi> Should we, at once, behold a glorious <hi>Sun</hi> at <hi>one</hi> hand brightly <hi>ſhining,</hi> in a ſerence, and clear day, with no <hi>Cloud</hi> interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and, on the <hi>other</hi> hand, the
<pb facs="tcp:32611:4"/>
               <hi>Moon</hi> totally <hi>eclipſed</hi> with thick, and black <hi>Clouds,</hi> o'reſpreading the whole face of the Heavens, from whence proceeded fearfull <hi>Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and <hi>Lightnings,</hi> with impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Storms,</hi> and <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> threatning another <hi>deluge</hi> of <hi>Waters</hi> to drown this <hi>great World</hi> again: how <hi>dreadfull</hi> would the one, and how <hi>amiable,</hi> and <hi>delightfull</hi> would the other ſeem? Grace of it <hi>ſelf</hi> is <hi>lovely;</hi> but, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>ſin,</hi> will look <hi>more lovely.</hi> So a <hi>gracious Woman,</hi> compar'd with one tht is <hi>graceleſs,</hi> how <hi>tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent?</hi> I humbly deſire Your <hi>Honours</hi> acception, and pardon, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Honours</hi> humble ſervant <hi>WILLIAM HARVEY,</hi> The meaneſt of them, that ſerve at the <hi>Altar.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32611:4"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE,</hi> AND <hi>VERT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> LADY, the LADY <hi>HILLIARD,</hi> of W. <hi>Horſly</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi> Grace, Mercey, <hi>and</hi> Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould I have left You out, I had been guilty of much <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;</hi> which is a thing ſo <hi>foul,</hi> as that <hi>alone</hi> objected, is ſufficient to make one <hi>odious</hi> to God, and man. Your <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip</hi> hath often ſupplyed my <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> and never did I return from You <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty.</hi> As <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> You have many a time made me <hi>go away rejoycing;</hi> for the <hi>Oil</hi> of Your <hi>Goodneſs</hi> never ſtayed ſo long, as there was a <hi>Veſſel</hi> more to receive it. I know Your <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip</hi> affects not <hi>Popularity:</hi> neither would have a <hi>Trumpet</hi> blown before You; being confident,
<pb facs="tcp:32611:5"/>that Your <hi>Right hand</hi> was ever ignorant of the <hi>Actions</hi> of Your <hi>Left.</hi> That God, which ſeeth in <hi>Secret,</hi> reward You <hi>openly.</hi> This is onely to expreſs my <hi>Thankfullneſs</hi> for all Your <hi>noble Favours;</hi> and to let the World know how much I am <hi>obliged</hi> to You. Again, who ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect <hi>Virtue,</hi> but the <hi>Virtuous?</hi> A glorious <hi>Frontiſpiece</hi> speaks ſomewhat <hi>within,</hi> and often begets a Deſire of <hi>Inſpection:</hi> So <hi>Virtue</hi> (We ſay) <hi>from a handſome, and comely Perſon, is more Acceptable;</hi> So <hi>Books</hi> owned, and protected by <hi>Noble</hi> Wights, have the better En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment from thoſe Hands they happen to fall into. But I will detain the <hi>Reader</hi> no longer: A <hi>Small City</hi> muſt have <hi>Gates</hi> proportionable, leſt it <hi>run out.</hi> Thus, in all Obſervance, I Reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Ladyſhips <hi>humble Servant</hi> WILLIAM HARVEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32611:5"/>
            <head>DIVINE MEDITATIONS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>Firſt <hi>Meditation upon</hi> Eve.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS was the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>us all,</hi> the <hi>Common Womb</hi> of the World. Here <hi>man</hi> had his firſt <hi>riſe,</hi> and <hi>deſcent.</hi> And, as <hi>Rivers</hi> come from the <hi>Sea;</hi> So all have their <hi>Breath</hi> from her. But, O my heart! As <hi>Jepthah</hi> brake out with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and <hi>Reluctancy,</hi> when his <hi>Daughter</hi> came out to meet him; So muſt we needs Say<note n="(a)" place="margin">Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, xi. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Aliſs,</hi> our Mother! <hi>thou haſt brought</hi> us <hi>very low,</hi> and <hi>thou art one of them, that troubleſt</hi> us.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32611:6"/>
                  <hi>Hinc illae lacrbymae!</hi> This is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of my <hi>Wo,</hi> and makes my <hi>tears</hi> trickle down, like a <hi>Shower</hi> of Rain. Thou waſt the <hi>cauſe</hi> of our <hi>life:</hi> true, we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it; But withall, through thy <hi>Fall,</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> World <hi>fell with thee.</hi> O the Sad <hi>Cataſtrophe!</hi> Into what a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>miſeries</hi> didſt thou plunge thy <hi>Progeny!</hi> Now nothing, but <hi>wringing</hi> of hands. <hi>In</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Matt. ii. 18.</note> Rama <hi>was there a voice heard, lamentation, and weeping,</hi> and <hi>great mourning;</hi> Rachel <hi>weeping for her Children, and would not be Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe they were not.</hi> Upon this thy <hi>lapſe</hi> it had been better for us, we had <hi>never</hi> been <hi>born,</hi> never ſeen the <hi>Sun,</hi> that glorious <hi>Lamp</hi> of Heaven. An Ugly <hi>Yoad,</hi> or fell <hi>Dragon</hi> is in a happier con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. All <hi>Senſitive,</hi> and <hi>Vegetative Creatures</hi> far tranſcend the <hi>Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> The <hi>eating</hi> of one <hi>Apple</hi> ſhook the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> and made the <hi>Stars</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32611:6"/>fall from heaven. By <hi>thee</hi> we loſt <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> not a <hi>Terreſtrial</hi> onely, but a <hi>Cel<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtial.</hi> — But this is not <hi>all:</hi> the one <hi>half</hi> of our miſeries is not told us. Our <hi>wretchedneſs,</hi> and infelicitie<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 King x. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>exceed the fame, that ye have heard.</hi> — How my <hi>Soul</hi> trembles! My <hi>Thoughts</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me, the <hi>joynts</hi> of my <hi>Loyns</hi> are looſed, and my <hi>Knees</hi> for <hi>fear</hi> ſmite one againſt another. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi>'s ſad <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> is <hi>ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Through <hi>thee,</hi> we loſt not <hi>heaven</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Poena Damni.</note> 
                  <hi>alone,</hi> enough to cauſe a <hi>Nabal</hi>'s heart to dye within him, and become like <hi>a Stone;</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe gained that of<note n="(e)" place="margin">Poena Senſus.</note> 
                  <hi>Senſe.</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſaiah! xxx. 33.</note> A <hi>Tophet,</hi> a <hi>Yelling,</hi> and <hi>Confuſed Pit</hi> made deep, and large; the <hi>Pile</hi> whereof is <hi>Fire,</hi> and much <hi>Wood;</hi> and the <hi>Breath</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> like a <hi>Stream</hi> of <hi>Brimſton,</hi> doth <hi>Kindle</hi> it. The <hi>prayer</hi> of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhall be ever mine. <hi>Here (O Lord) bu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> me to aſhes, cut my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32611:7"/>body to pieces, that thou mayeſt ſave me for the future. O, let my Soul live with Thee, and no matter, though I ſuffer in this world a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand exquiſite deaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Job. xxxviii. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>But who is this, that darkens Counſel without Knowledge?</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Chap. xl. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Once have I ſpoken, but I will not anſwer; yea twice but, I will proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> How is <hi>wretched man</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum multa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ab illo!</note> 
                  <hi>altered!</hi> What a <hi>glorious change</hi> upon the Sudden! The heavens <hi>Smile</hi> upon us, all is <hi>Serene,</hi> and <hi>clear.</hi> No dire <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> or dark <hi>Cloud,</hi> to obſcure our <hi>Sun.</hi> Man, reaſſume thy <hi>Courage;</hi> Wipe of the <hi>Tears</hi> from thy <hi>Cheeks;</hi> behold, a <hi>harmeleſs Dove</hi> comes to thee with an <hi>Olive branch</hi> in her mouth, and the <hi>Waters</hi> are abated. O <hi>golden</hi> Sentence!<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen. iii. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>The Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpent's head.</hi> No <hi>Honey,</hi> or <hi>Honey-Comb</hi> ſo Sweet. I am even Raviſhed with the <hi>Contemplation,</hi> and as it were
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32611:7"/>
                  <hi>rapt into</hi> the <hi>third Heaven.</hi> Now <hi>Satan</hi> do thy worſt, thy <hi>Venom</hi> is ſpit.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. cxlvi. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Praiſe, ye the</hi> Lord: <hi>Praiſe the</hi> Lord, <hi>O my Soul! While I live, will I praiſe the</hi> Lord! <hi>I will Sing praiſes unto my</hi> God, <hi>while I have any being.—Eve,</hi> thou haſt now given us <hi>Heaped meaſure, preſsed down,</hi> and <hi>running over.</hi> A full <hi>Compenſation</hi> haſt thou made us. <hi>Thy,</hi> and <hi>our God,</hi> hath cauſed thee to be <hi>Inſtrumental</hi> in our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration.</hi> By <hi>Faith</hi> in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to <hi>come,</hi> art thou Saved; and we by <hi>Faith</hi> in him, as <hi>Come</hi> already, <hi>dead, buried, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> and <hi>aſcended</hi> into heaven. — In thy State of <hi>Innocency</hi> thou hadſt <hi>free will,</hi> but ſubject to <hi>temptation.</hi> Yet thy Fault was <hi>freely</hi> perpetrated, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Coaction.</hi> Thou hadſt <hi>power</hi> from <hi>above</hi> to <hi>Stand;</hi> thank thy <hi>Self</hi> for thy <hi>fall. Thy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is of thy ſelf,</hi> O Iſrael! <hi>Sweet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32611:8"/>Father,</hi> whom thou loveſt <hi>now,</hi> thou loveſt <hi>ever.</hi> We may <hi>fall</hi> into <hi>Sin,</hi> and fall <hi>again;</hi> but not <hi>finally,</hi> nor <hi>totally.</hi> Thy <hi>Promiſes</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> are <hi>without Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance:</hi> like the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> they <hi>alter</hi> not. <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but Thy word ſhall not</hi> fail.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Lord,</hi> Support us with thy <hi>Grace,</hi> and Sweet <hi>Influences</hi> of thy bleſſed <hi>Spirit;</hi> that we fall into <hi>no</hi> Sin. <hi>If thou</hi> forſtake <hi>us, we</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Let him, that thinketh he ſtands, take heed, leſt he fall.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Cloath us with <hi>Humility,</hi> as with a <hi>Garment,</hi> and make us <hi>Senſible</hi> of the heavy <hi>Weight</hi> of our Sins. As <hi>weary,</hi> and <hi>heavy-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> let us make to him, who took <hi>our Tranſgreſsions</hi> upon him, that knew <hi>no</hi> Sin, that <hi>we</hi> may have <hi>Reſt,</hi> even the <hi>forgiveneſs</hi> of all our Sins, leſt they ſink us into <hi>irrecoverable</hi> Perdition. <hi>O</hi> Jeſu, <hi>sis mihi</hi> Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32611:8"/>
               <head>2. Meditation <hi>upon</hi> Sarah.</head>
               <p>THis may be the World's <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> or the <hi>Females Tutoureſs,</hi> to learn her <hi>Sex</hi> Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. She knew well, that <hi>Man</hi> was not made for the <hi>Woman;</hi> but the contrary: and therefore tends the <hi>end</hi> of her <hi>Creation.</hi> She ſcorns to ſtand in <hi>Competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with her <hi>Husband;</hi> but nulls a <hi>paritie,</hi> and calls him <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Scanctified Woman</hi> is a <hi>rare Creature;</hi> having more <hi>Luſtre</hi> in her, then any <hi>twinkling Star.</hi> How <hi>calm</hi> the <hi>Sea</hi> is, when there's no <hi>wind</hi> ſtirring! Her <hi>houſe</hi> is as Silent, as the <hi>night.</hi> There is no <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con;</hi> for no ſooner <hi>ſaid,</hi> but <hi>done. Happy</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> in the fruition of ſuch a <hi>Wife.</hi> He is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prov. xxxi, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>known in the Gates, when he ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth among the Elders of the Lord.</hi> No <hi>Harmony</hi> like to <hi>Still-Muſick.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32611:9"/>The Man <hi>eats, drinks,</hi> and <hi>ſleeps</hi> in quiet. No <hi>diſturbance,</hi> where there is ſuch a <hi>Conſort;</hi> for his <hi>days</hi> are <hi>prolonged;</hi> he <hi>dyes in peace,</hi> and is <hi>gathered to his Fathers in a good old age.</hi> Here's an <hi>help meet</hi> for him; becauſe in <hi>two</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Bodies</hi> there's but <hi>one Soul.</hi> O, what <hi>Contentment</hi> is there, where there is ſuch an <hi>accord!</hi> In ſuch a <hi>well-tuned Inſtrument</hi> there can be no <hi>flaw;</hi> but every <hi>Touch</hi> enchanteth the <hi>ear,</hi> and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts <hi>attention.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To you then, whoſe <hi>Lot</hi> is fallen into ſo <hi>fair a ground;</hi> Be not you <hi>Imperial,</hi> and <hi>unnatural.</hi> Prove not <hi>unkind</hi> to a <hi>Spouſe</hi> ſo <hi>lovely,</hi> who hath made you all, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Pompeys,</hi> nad <hi>Caeſars.</hi> Return <hi>love</hi> for <hi>love,</hi> and grieve not, <hi>cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> ſo <hi>harmleſs</hi> a Creature. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not a <hi>Tear</hi> to ſully ſo <hi>Sweet</hi> a Face; but tender her <hi>contentment,</hi> as the <hi>Apple</hi> of your <hi>Eye.</hi> Who,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32611:9"/>in his <hi>right Wits,</hi> would <hi>injure</hi> ſuch a <hi>Bed-fellow?</hi> Compare <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> with a <hi>perverſe</hi> woman to <hi>Such</hi> a Wife: and what a <hi>vaſt dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion!</hi> If ever there was a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe on Earth,</hi> it's <hi>here.</hi> Except the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and the <hi>Joys of Heaven</hi> alone, to ſuch a woman there is no <hi>compare.</hi> Let no <hi>Churl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Nabal</hi> ever kiſs her <hi>Lips;</hi> much leſs crop the <hi>flower</hi> of her <hi>Youth.</hi> A <hi>Wight,</hi> ſo <hi>rarely</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, let no <hi>rude</hi> hand attempt once to touch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>3. Meditation upon <hi>Rebekah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOdeſt, and faithfull <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah,</hi> thou comeſt next to hand, a <hi>Daughter</hi> well becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a <hi>Mother.</hi> Thou ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not thy kind; for thou enjoyeſt her <hi>vertues.</hi> Thou, Chaſt <hi>Penelope!</hi> How many may <hi>bluſh</hi> to read
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32611:10"/>thee! The unplucked <hi>Roſe,</hi> and <hi>Lilly,</hi> not more pure. No <hi>Snow</hi> in <hi>Salmon</hi> whiter. Thou waſt as <hi>innocent,</hi> as a <hi>new-born</hi> Babe; <hi>true,</hi> as the <hi>Turtle-done</hi> to her Mate; and, though <hi>married,</hi> ever a <hi>Virgin.</hi> Like <hi>Joſeph,</hi> thou wert of <hi>Canon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof,</hi> and no aſſault could once <hi>Seale</hi> thy Walls. As a <hi>well-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plined</hi> Army, none could break thy Ranks; but alwaies thou putteſt the <hi>Enemy</hi> to a rout.— O thou <hi>one of a thouſand!</hi> unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell'd, incomparable woman! What <hi>Bays</hi> ſufficient to <hi>Crown</hi> thy Temples? Thy memory is <hi>Sweet,</hi> and <hi>Lovely:</hi> and thy <hi>choſt</hi> fellows praiſe thee. How an I <hi>tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> with thee? My <hi>Genius</hi> promp me: and yet, alaſs! my <hi>Pen</hi> falls ſhort of her encomiums.—</p>
               <p>Look into this <hi>Proſpective,</hi> you <hi>weaker</hi> veſſels, behold a <hi>lively</hi> pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for your imitation. Caſt your eyes upon this <hi>Sampler,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32611:10"/>write after this <hi>fair Copy.</hi> Your <hi>Bodies</hi> are the <hi>Temples</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> defile them not then. No <hi>unclean</hi> thing can enter heaven. Shake off your <hi>Paramours,</hi> if you love your <hi>Souls,</hi> and be faithfull to your <hi>married</hi> beds. Wrong not your <hi>Husbands,</hi> your own <hi>fleſh,</hi> your precious <hi>Souls.</hi> It will be <hi>bitterneſs</hi> in the later end, believe me. God is <hi>pure,</hi> and hates all <hi>uncleanneſs.</hi> Caſt not away that <hi>better part,</hi> which is capable of Immortality. Your pleaſures are but <hi>momentary,</hi> which, ſo ſoon, as injoyed, vaniſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>4. Meditations upon <hi>Abigail.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIſe <hi>Abigail,</hi> thou art now my <hi>Subject,</hi> pity, a <hi>Fool</hi> ſhould have been thy <hi>Huſband;</hi> for <hi>Nabal</hi> was <hi>his name,</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> was <hi>with him.</hi> He was a <hi>Churl</hi> too, that, hadſt thou not been <hi>wiſe, one</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32611:11"/>houſe had been too little for both. A <hi>Crooked</hi> piece of Timber ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time is in a <hi>fair</hi> Building, and a <hi>perverſe</hi> man my have a <hi>compleat</hi> woman; elſe the whole <hi>Fabrick</hi> would fall.—This is none of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> bleſſings, had a man but eyes to ſee it. Setting the <hi>Grace of God</hi> aſide, and the <hi>orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> a <hi>vertuous</hi> woman hath no <hi>Peer.</hi>—See how this <hi>fair Water</hi> quencheth the violence of <hi>Fire. David</hi> is reſolved to cut off <hi>root,</hi> and <hi>branch,</hi> all that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to <hi>Nabal.</hi> Like <hi>Jehu</hi> he marcheth <hi>Furiouſly,</hi> intent upon <hi>Revenge,</hi> for the unmanly affront of that <hi>Fool.</hi> She preſently goes forth to encounter him, a <hi>weak woman</hi> with a <hi>man</hi> of <hi>war.</hi> Hear her <hi>Rhetorick.</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Sam. xxv. 24, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon me, my LORD, upon me let this Iniquity be,</hi> and <hi>let thine Handmaid, I pray thee, ſpeak in thine audience,</hi> and <hi>hear the words of thine Handmaid,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:32611:11"/>&amp;c. Not a <hi>word,</hi> but hath its <hi>weight,</hi> and <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> Good God, how <hi>immenſe</hi> is <hi>thy</hi> wiſdome, when a poor <hi>woman</hi> is ſo <hi>rare!</hi> Needs muſt thou, our <hi>Creatour,</hi> be wiſe, when a Silly <hi>Creature</hi> is ſo accompliſhed. This Wiſdome was that wiſdome, which was <hi>from above, pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie-to-be-intreated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>James</hi> iii. 17. Like the <hi>holy cyl,</hi> with which the <hi>veſſels</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> were anointed, it had the <hi>beſt Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents.</hi> Here was no <hi>Machiavellian</hi> Policy, or <hi>Cromwellian.</hi> Stand off, ye <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Belial,</hi> you <hi>brats</hi> of a <hi>perverſe woman. Her</hi> Tongue was touched with <hi>a coal form</hi> the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: theirs</hi> ſet <hi>on fire of h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, earthly, Senſual, Deviliſh.</hi> The <hi>S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> now makes for the <hi>Cloak.</hi> She attempts it, and effects it. As a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain <hi>dam</hi> reared up, ſhe turns the <hi>Torrent</hi> another way. A bleſſed Succeſs! See, how <hi>low</hi> are the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32611:12"/>now? <hi>Jordan</hi> is driven <hi>back:</hi> and that face, which was once <hi>Terrible,</hi> now <hi>Smiles.</hi> Not one <hi>drop</hi> of blood ſpilt. The <hi>big</hi> Mountain is delivered of a <hi>mouſe.</hi> What <hi>Inſtrument</hi> ſo mean, but ſucceeds through <hi>divine</hi> aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. <hi>Abigail,</hi> thou plaiedſt thy part well, and wenteſt of the <hi>Stage</hi> with a <hi>Plaudit.</hi> Thou wert not unrewarded neither, for thy <hi>Share</hi> was much; the <hi>Corydon</hi> dyes, and in his room ſtepps up a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>5. Meditations upon <hi>Naomi,</hi> and <hi>Ruth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre are <hi>a pair</hi> of <hi>Vertues;</hi> they go <hi>hand in hand,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> God ſerves them <hi>both. Ruth,</hi> happy for thee, thou met teſt with ſuch a <hi>Mother;</hi> and <hi>Naomi,</hi> no leſs happy wert thou, in having ſuch a <hi>Daughter.</hi> Call thy Self
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32611:12"/>no more <hi>Mara;</hi> for thy <hi>Daughter-in-law,</hi> which loved thee, was <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved</hi> of God. How <hi>wonderfull</hi> are thy <hi>waies,</hi> O <hi>Lord,</hi> How <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable</hi> thy <hi>Goodneſs!</hi> God is no <hi>reſpecter of perſons;</hi> but whom he will ſave ſhall be ſaved, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſaith <hi>Nay.</hi> No <hi>reaſon</hi> can be ſhewn<note n="(a)" place="margin">Stat pro ratione voluntas.</note> for it, but this, <hi>It is his will, his pleaſure.</hi> Thus the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> concludes. <hi>So them, it is not of him, that willeth, nor of him, that runneth; but of God, that ſheweth mercy.</hi> Rom. ix. 16.</p>
               <p>How <hi>Attractive</hi> is <hi>Heaven!</hi> How doth <hi>Grace</hi> add <hi>wings,</hi> where there were <hi>leaden heels</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore! How greedily doth ſhe now <hi>Swallow</hi> that, which once her <hi>Stomack loathed.</hi> For a <hi>Moab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite</hi> to become an <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> an <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later,</hi> a <hi>true worſhipper</hi> of God; a <hi>Devil,</hi> a <hi>Saint;</hi> and that upon the ſuddain, is a ſtrange <hi>Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis.</hi> All the <hi>Blocks</hi> in her way
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32611:13"/>ſhe removes. Neither her <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, people,</hi> her <hi>Siſter-in-law,</hi> who returned back, nor her <hi>Gods</hi> can ſtay her progreſs. The place ſhe went to, ſhe knew not, all were <hi>Strangers</hi> to her; beſides this, ſhe was in a <hi>wanting</hi> Condition: yet none of theſe can <hi>ſtop</hi> her.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ruth. i. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>For whither thou goeſt, I will go; and where thou lodgeſt, I will lodge; thy people ſhall be my people, and thy God, my God.</hi> No <hi>relation</hi> can obſtruct thoſe, whom God means to call. Now they arrive at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> yet <hi>poor,</hi> and <hi>indigent.—Faith</hi> gives us no <hi>Charter</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt us from <hi>poverty.</hi> This <hi>Lot</hi> often falls upon God's <hi>deareſt</hi> children. <hi>Affliction</hi> commonly is their <hi>Coviator,</hi> their <hi>fellow-traveller,</hi> and <hi>companion.</hi> Yet, in this <hi>low Ebb,</hi> they were not dejected; nor <hi>forſaken</hi> of God. The <hi>Young</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>gleans</hi> in the field of <hi>Boaz,</hi> &amp; God gives her <hi>favour</hi> in his Sight,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32611:13"/>under whoſe <hi>Wings</hi> of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhe came to <hi>Shrowd.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any, that <hi>truſted</hi> in him, was <hi>confounded.</hi> Will God ſhake them off, that <hi>cling</hi> unto him? Can a <hi>natural Mother</hi> ſee her Child cry after her, and her <hi>Bowels</hi> not <hi>yearn</hi> upon it? Much leſs, will God turn his <hi>back</hi> upon thoſe, who make ſuch haſte after him. But ſee how the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of the Lord <hi>dogs</hi> her, and follows her <hi>ſtep by ſtep.</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ruth iii.</note> 
                  <hi>My daughter, ſhall I not ſeek reſt for thee, that it may be well with thee?</hi> Here's <hi>no love loſt</hi> (as we uſe to ſay) a full <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation</hi> is made, and an ample <hi>retribution.</hi> Mark this, you <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> women, and <hi>dye</hi> your Cheeks into a <hi>bluſh.</hi> Hang down your <hi>heads,</hi> for ſhame, you <hi>dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate</hi> Mothers, you <hi>Maſculine</hi> Creatures, and Stony <hi>Niobes.</hi> The <hi>oſtrich</hi> lays her <hi>Eggs,</hi> and then leaves them to the mercy of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32611:14"/>
                  <hi>Traveller;</hi> So, many <hi>procreate</hi> Children, and leave them at <hi>Six,</hi> and <hi>Sevens,</hi> to <hi>Sink,</hi> or <hi>Swim,</hi> all's one to them. Is this <hi>Religion?</hi> Is this all the <hi>fruits</hi> of their <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi> The ſavage <hi>Bears</hi> are more <hi>natural;</hi> for they <hi>lick</hi> their <hi>young</hi> into a form, and are indulgent to them. One would not think ſo <hi>ſweet</hi> a Creature was ſo <hi>Cruel.</hi> But 'tis no <hi>News,</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Latet anguis ſub Herba.</note> for a <hi>Snake</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to ly under the <hi>Smooth Graſs;</hi> and for <hi>Sodom</hi>'s <hi>Golden Apples</hi> to vaniſh into <hi>Smoak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To proceed, <hi>Ruth</hi> obeys her <hi>Mother,</hi> comes ſoftly to <hi>Boaz, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers</hi> his <hi>feet,</hi> and lays her <hi>down</hi> by him. The man awakes, and is <hi>afraid</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Ruth iii. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> am <hi>Ruth thine hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid</hi> (ſaies ſhe) <hi>Spread therefore the Skirt over thine Hand-maid; for thou</hi> art <hi>a near Kinſman.</hi> She ventures hard, and puts to <hi>Sea;</hi> but, God giving her a favourable wind, makes a <hi>good voyage,</hi> returns
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32611:14"/>to <hi>Naomi</hi> Richly-laden, with a promiſe from <hi>Boaz,</hi> to perform the part of a <hi>kinſman</hi> to her. — Take the <hi>Reſult</hi> of all. The <hi>Marriage</hi> is <hi>Solemnized</hi> with Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of Joy; a general <hi>Conſent,</hi> and <hi>Content,</hi> and ſhe, who, of late, <hi>gleaned</hi> a few <hi>ears</hi> after the <hi>Reapers,</hi> is now <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of the <hi>whole field. — Religion,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty</hi> is a fair <hi>Portion;</hi> and weighs more with <hi>Wiſe</hi> men, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Wealth,</hi> or <hi>Beauty.</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Gen. xiv. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Give me the</hi> Perſons, <hi>and take the</hi> goods <hi>to thy Self,</hi> ſaid the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> So, for My part, give me the <hi>Woman,</hi> and let who will, take the <hi>Portion,</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi> to himſelf. Though, I confeſs, when all concurr in one, theſe <hi>Simples</hi> make an excellent <hi>Compound.</hi> Yet, put <hi>Vertue</hi> into one <hi>Scale,</hi> and the reſt in the <hi>other;</hi> it weighes them <hi>all down</hi> to nothing. — <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omi,</hi> thy <hi>Daughter</hi> now is better
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32611:15"/>to thee, then <hi>Seven Sons;</hi> for ſhe is thy <hi>Support</hi> in thine <hi>old-age.</hi> As choice <hi>Spirits</hi> of <hi>Life, ſhe</hi> ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens thy <hi>feeble knees. Goodwas it for</hi> thee <hi>to be afflicted; for</hi> thou muſt now confeſs, with that Sweet <hi>Singer of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thy Rod,</hi> and <hi>thy Staff comfort me.</hi> To <hi>Conclude,</hi> their <hi>Lives</hi> were <hi>Tragic mical,</hi> a <hi>Medly,</hi> a <hi>Compoſition</hi> of <hi>Sowr</hi> and <hi>Sweet.</hi> Yet, though their day was ſomewhat <hi>dark</hi> &amp; <hi>gloomy,</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-down of their Sun was <hi>clear.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Meditations upon the</hi> Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nammite.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarity,</hi> I ſeldom meet with thee, and therefore we muſt not part ſo. <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs</hi> to meet in one, is a <hi>glorious</hi> fight. <hi>To do good to all is our Duty; but eſpecially to the hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould of Faith.</hi> The <hi>Object</hi> adds Luſtre to it, and <hi>Crowns</hi> it. This
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32611:15"/>
                  <hi>Woman</hi> hath ſcarce her <hi>fellow:</hi> which puts me in mind of that <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Philoſophie,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Nul ſimile eſt idem.</note> 
                  <hi>No like is the ſame.</hi> Let us come to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. — <hi>And it fell on a day, that</hi> Eliſha <hi>paſſed</hi> to Shunem, <hi>where was a Great Woman, and ſhe comp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lled him to eat bread.</hi> I muſt ſtop at this <hi>middle</hi> point. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him,</hi> ſaid I? Is there ſuch an one living? It's a rare Bird upon Earth then, ſomewhat like a <hi>black Swan.</hi> 'Tis well now adays, if <hi>Importunity</hi> gets any thing. Were the <hi>Prophet</hi> living now, he would hardly finde the like entertainment. He might implore the <hi>Charity</hi> of ſome <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males,</hi> who are called <hi>Chriſtans too,</hi> (but <hi>Ironice</hi>) untill his <hi>heart aked,</hi> and with them<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 King. xviii. 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Cry aloud</hi> from <hi>Morning</hi> till <hi>Noon,</hi> and from <hi>Noon</hi> till <hi>Night,</hi> and yet have no <hi>voice,</hi> nor any to <hi>anſwer,</hi> nor any, that regarded. The <hi>Prophets</hi> fare
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32611:16"/>worſe, then any, in our late Times of <hi>Reformation,</hi> or rather <hi>Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> they, with the <hi>weakeſt,</hi> ever <hi>went to the Wall,</hi> unleſs ſome <hi>confiding Boys,</hi> with their <hi>Shel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> upon them, who ſhould have gone to <hi>Jericho</hi> till their <hi>Beards</hi> had grown; Or Such old <hi>Peny-Fathers,</hi> thoſe excellent <hi>Tex<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uaries,</hi> and <hi>Boanerges,</hi> who could <hi>baul</hi> loudeſt <hi>Curſe ye Meroz.</hi> Theſe indeed were fed at <hi>Jezebel's Talbe.</hi> No <hi>Muzzel-man</hi> among the <hi>Turks</hi> in higher eſteem. The <hi>poor Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhas,</hi> as if they had the Curſe of <hi>Elie</hi>'s <hi>Poſterity,</hi> were fain to <hi>crouch</hi> for a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>Silver,</hi> and a <hi>Morſel</hi> of <hi>Bread.</hi> So ſad was their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ſo <hi>deplorable.</hi> — But my <hi>Shunammite,</hi> thou <hi>Sanctified</hi> Woman, and Glory of thy <hi>Sex;</hi> thou hadſt a <hi>better Spirit,</hi> to the Shame of <hi>future Ages,</hi> and to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle an holy zeal of <hi>Emulation</hi> in nobler Souls.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:32611:16"/>
               <p> Yet this is but <hi>poſitive</hi> all the while; She aſcends a <hi>degree</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>And ſo it was, as oft as he paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by, he turned in thither to eat bread.</hi> — She was not <hi>weary</hi> of <hi>welldoing;</hi> but, like the <hi>Sun,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to <hi>Run her courſe.</hi> She was none of thoſe, that give a <hi>bit,</hi> and a <hi>knock:</hi> and ſhe Scorned to return that <hi>Common,</hi> and <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious</hi> Objection, <hi>You were here once before.</hi> Grace is <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and, like the <hi>Widon</hi>'s <hi>Oil,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtops ſo long, as there is a <hi>veſſel</hi> more to receive it. <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> in <hi>Goodneſs</hi> makes a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> compleat. <hi>You did run well, who did hinder you;</hi> Gal. v. 7. Many for a <hi>Spirt</hi> run <hi>Swiftly,</hi> their <hi>Setting cut</hi> is <hi>Violent,</hi> but that's not <hi>perpetual,</hi> like <hi>Jades,</hi> they are ſoon tired, the <hi>Chariot-wheels</hi> of their <hi>Devotion</hi> are taken off, that, at laſt, they <hi>drive heavily,</hi> One <hi>jeeringly</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannibal;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32611:17"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hannibal,</hi>
                        <note n="(c)" place="margin">Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſcis, Hannibal, uti Victoria neſcis.</note> to get the Victory thou know'ſt full well,</l>
                     <l>But after how to uſe't, thou can'ſt not tell.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To begin in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and to end in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> is to no purpoſe; we loſe both our <hi>Oil,</hi> and <hi>Toyl.</hi> Not to go <hi>forward</hi> is to go <hi>back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> The <hi>Exit</hi> proves all our <hi>actions,</hi> and <hi>Crowns</hi> the <hi>Play</hi> — To make her <hi>Superlative,</hi> and I have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us make a little Chamber, I pray thee, on the Wall, and let us ſet for him there a Bed, and a Table, and a Stool, and a Candle-ſtick: and it ſhall be, when he cometh to us, that he ſhall turn in thither.</hi> I ſhould ſcarce have given Credit to it, had it not been Recorded in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ.</hi> And I awake yet, or in a dream? I can but admire yet at this <hi>Arabian Bird,</hi> when I compare her with the <hi>Scornfull
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32611:17"/>Dames</hi> of this Age. A <hi>Dancing-Maſter,</hi> or a <hi>Fidler,</hi> hath free <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, Egreſs,</hi> and <hi>Regreſs,</hi> when the poor <hi>man of God</hi> muſt ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and blow his <hi>fingers;</hi> for he hath no <hi>pottage</hi> to cool. Out come the <hi>ſervants,</hi> this <hi>Gill,</hi> and that <hi>Flurt, Cerberus</hi> the Porter, whoſe <hi>Fathers they would ſometime have ſcorned to ſet with the dogs of their ſtock,</hi> (as holy <hi>Job</hi> once ſaid in his <hi>agony,</hi> Job. xxx. I.) and they look on them as ſowr as a <hi>Carb.</hi> The <hi>Prophets</hi> have not a word to ſay being firſt ſeen by the <hi>Baſilisks,</hi> and ſtand dumb as <hi>Planet-ſtruck. Democritus Juniour</hi> ſaw how it was with the <hi>Miniſters</hi> in his time, when he brake out in theſe words:
<q>
                     <l>Dat <hi>Galenus</hi>
                        <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in his <hi>Preface</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                        </note> opes, dat <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinianus</hi> honores;</l>
                     <l>Sed <hi>Genus</hi> &amp; <hi>Species</hi> Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turire pedes.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:32611:18"/>
                     <l>The rich <hi>Phyſician,</hi> honoured <hi>Lawyer</hi> Rides,</l>
                     <l>Whil'ſt the poor <hi>Scholler</hi> foots it by their <hi>Sides.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But for the <hi>Scum</hi> of the World, the <hi>Riff-raff,</hi> every baſe <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> &amp; <hi>Trencher-waiter,</hi> to affront, and ſcorn the <hi>Ambaſsadours</hi> of the <hi>moſt High,</hi> is a <hi>Sin</hi> tranſcendent, a <hi>Shame</hi> to Religion, and an <hi>hiſſing</hi> to the whole earth. — Pardon me, you <hi>more Noble Wights,</hi> and forgive me this wrong. Some of you have taken in the poor wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Levite,</hi> and, with <hi>Obadiah,</hi> have fed the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Prophets</hi> with <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Water. Samaritan</hi> like, you have poured <hi>oil</hi> into the deep <hi>wounds</hi> of many, that have been <hi>half-dead</hi> in miſery, ready to breath out their <hi>laſt.</hi> You <hi>have given drink unto them, that were ready to periſh, and wine unto thoſe, that were of heavy hearts, that they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32611:18"/>might drink, and forget their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; and remember their miſery no more.</hi> Prov. xxxi. 6, 7. This you did, to your <hi>Perpetual praiſe,</hi> and let his <hi>Right-hand forget his Cunning,</hi> that proves <hi>ingrate.</hi> Here was ſome <hi>Intermiſſion</hi> of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> a time of <hi>breathing,</hi> had not that <hi>wild goard</hi> marr'd the <hi>pottage,</hi> that they could eat no more of it. Let them ever be an <hi>hiſſing,</hi> a <hi>by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word,</hi> and a <hi>Proverb</hi> to all <hi>after-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> that were the firſt breakers of this peace, who Reſolved upon the Queſtion, <hi>That no ſuffering</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <hi>in the cauſe of God, and his King, ſhould have Houſe, or Home, or where to lay his head.</hi> — You Pretenders of <hi>Reformation,</hi> you wicked <hi>Hamans,</hi> and Sons of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meda<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ha,</hi> you <hi>Cannibals,</hi> and <hi>blood-sucking Horſe-leaches:</hi> the <hi>pit,</hi> which ye have digg'd for <hi>others,</hi> you may chance fall into your ſelves. Look to in, for as ſure, <hi>as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32611:19"/>the Lord liveth,</hi> the <hi>ſame meaſure</hi> will be meaſured to <hi>you</hi> again, if you repent not. There is a <hi>God,</hi> that ſits in heaven, ſhall <hi>laugh you to Scorn,</hi> and <hi>have you in deriſion.</hi> But this by way of <hi>digreſſion.</hi> To our <hi>subject.</hi> God, who will not let a Cup of <hi>Cold water</hi> paſs <hi>unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded,</hi> returns a bleſſing <hi>equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</hi> For her <hi>charity,</hi> he fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies her <hi>womb,</hi> and gives her a <hi>Son.</hi> Never was <hi>Bread</hi> yet <hi>caſt upon the waters,</hi> but in <hi>due time</hi> it was <hi>found</hi> again. <hi>He, that giveth to the poor, lendeth unto the Lord, and he will repay</hi> it. The <hi>Sea</hi> ſupplies all <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> and yet is full; the <hi>Sun</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Heat</hi> to all <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunaries</hi> without <hi>Subſtraction; One Candle</hi> lights <hi>many,</hi> and no <hi>diminution:</hi> So <hi>Charity,</hi> (though thought <hi>prodigal</hi>) is a <hi>full Sea,</hi> a <hi>tranſparent Sur,</hi> and a <hi>Candle not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extinguiſh'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:32611:19"/>
               <head>Meditaion on <hi>Bath-ſheba.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FAir <hi>Venus</hi> had a <hi>Mole,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> ſometime is <hi>Eclipſ'd,</hi> the <hi>Moon</hi> in her <hi>Wane,</hi> and thou, <hi>Bath-ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> (though otherwiſe vertuous) hadſt thy failings. I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly go backward, and cover thy <hi>nakedneſs,</hi> ſhould I not be thought <hi>partial.</hi> Yet I will not <hi>blaze</hi> thee to thy <hi>ſhame,</hi> but, as a <hi>Mercurie</hi>'s finger, ſet thee up, to direct all <hi>Travailers</hi> the <hi>right</hi> way. Thou did'ſt <hi>waſh</hi> thy ſelf; ſo thou <hi>mighteſt,</hi> who ſhould hinder thee? But herein thou <hi>erredſt;</hi> it was too <hi>publick,</hi> thou wert <hi>viſible,</hi> the <hi>King<hi>ſaw thee, and thy <hi>Beauty charmed</hi> him. My <hi>Conſtruction</hi> of thee ſhall be <hi>Candid.</hi> I believe thou didſt it not to that intent, to <hi>blow that fire,</hi> which was apt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>kindle</hi> of it ſelf, neither didſt thou imagine thy <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32611:20"/>a <hi>ſpectatour.</hi> But thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have been more <hi>private,</hi> and this <hi>miſchief</hi> has not happened.— Of all the <hi>Senſes,</hi> the <hi>Eye</hi> is moſt <hi>affective,</hi> and what <hi>Poyſon</hi> pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates the <hi>Heart,</hi> is let in at that <hi>Window.</hi> No <hi>object</hi> more <hi>attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive,</hi> then <hi>Beauty;</hi> for, be the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> never ſo <hi>hard,</hi> this <hi>Load-ſtone</hi> will <hi>draw</hi> it. Nothing hath been able to divert the <hi>Current</hi> of this <hi>ſtream.</hi> What <hi>Remora</hi> can put a ſtop to ſuch a <hi>Veſſel</hi> in its <hi>Carrier? Samſon</hi> could ſlay a <hi>thouſand Men</hi> with the <hi>Jaw-bone</hi> of an <hi>Aſs,</hi> and yet one <hi>Delilah</hi> makes an <hi>Aſs</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> puts out both his <hi>Eyes,</hi> ſo that he <hi>grinds at the Mill</hi> and becomes <hi>ridiculons</hi> to the <hi>uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Philiſtines.</hi> When that <hi>Wretch Balaam</hi> could no way <hi>curſe</hi> the people of God, he puts this <hi>Stumbling-block</hi> before them, and they preſently <hi>fall.</hi> This <hi>She-Divel</hi> puts them more to a <hi>rout,</hi>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32611:20"/>then an <hi>hoſt</hi> of <hi>armed</hi> men. <hi>Solomon</hi> was <hi>Wiſe,</hi> yet in his <hi>old Age</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a <hi>Child again,</hi> his <hi>wife</hi> draws his <hi>heart</hi> from the <hi>living Lord,</hi> and he falls down to an <hi>Idol.</hi> One <hi>wanton Helen,</hi> in <hi>ten</hi> years Wars, <hi>cauſed</hi> a ſlaughter of more, then a <hi>Million</hi> of Men. What ſhould I ſay more? The <hi>Triumphs,</hi> and <hi>Victories,</hi> obtained by this thing called <hi>Woman,</hi> no <hi>Tongue</hi> is able to expreſs. This <hi>Wiſh</hi> of <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> to his <hi>Friend</hi> ſhall be mine. —<hi>The Omnipotent God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee from an Omnipotent Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> — But let's not do <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba</hi> too much wrong neither. She did not <hi>proſtitute</hi> her ſelf, as a <hi>Mercenary Strumpet.</hi> No; ſhe was ſtrongly <hi>Courted,</hi> and <hi>Imporiuned,</hi> and that by a <hi>King.</hi> Which <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> leſſen her <hi>Fault,</hi> and <hi>extenuate</hi> her <hi>ſin.</hi> — She was no <hi>Shutile-Cock,</hi> or <hi>Tennis-ball,</hi> to be <hi>toſſed,</hi> and <hi>banded</hi> by every <hi>Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:32611:21"/>but like a <hi>Royal fort</hi> won by <hi>ſtorm.</hi> Who can waſh their hands in <hi>innocency?</hi> They, that are <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin,</hi> let them <hi>throw the firſt ſtone.</hi> Good <hi>God!</hi> what are we without thy <hi>ſupporting hand,</hi> without <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Grace?</hi> If thou <hi>forſakeſt</hi> us, we <hi>fall.</hi>
                        <note n="(a)" place="margin">Vae ettam lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibili vitae hominum; Si, remota miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcutias ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> Miſerable were that <hi>Converſation,</hi> though never ſo <hi>pure,</hi> if thou ſhouldſt examine it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Compaſſionate</hi> Ey. Much Droſs</hi> would be found in the <hi>fineſt Gold,</hi> when it comes to the <hi>fire.</hi> What is a <hi>blinking Candle</hi> to the <hi>Sun?</hi> How deformed, and foul would an <hi>Ethiopian</hi> ſeem, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with an <hi>exquiſite beauty? The very Angels are not pure in his Sight.</hi> Strike we then our <hi>Top-ſails,</hi> and let us <hi>vailour Bonnets,</hi> Down with your <hi>Tails,</hi> you <hi>Birds</hi> of <hi>Juno,</hi> and proud <hi>Peacocks;</hi> caſt your <hi>Crowns</hi> before his <hi>Throne,</hi> fall <hi>down</hi> before him, and <hi>worſhip</hi> him, that ſits on it, <hi>who liveth forever, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32611:21"/>ever.</hi> — Let me give this <hi>Caveat</hi> onely to either <hi>Sex;</hi> and I have done. — And firſt, to you, the <hi>weaker. Cloath</hi> your ſelves with <hi>Modeſtie,</hi> as <hi>with a Garment;</hi> Shun all occaſions of <hi>Sin,</hi> admit not any <hi>Laſcivious em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace;</hi> frown upon all <hi>Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that tend to <hi>diſhonour;</hi> and, <hi>Baſilisk</hi> like, ſtrike them <hi>dumb</hi> with looks. Who dare ſpeak <hi>obſcenely</hi> to a <hi>Chaſt Ear,</hi> or lay <hi>Rude hands</hi> on a reſolved <hi>Spirit?</hi> A <hi>Caſtle,</hi> which ſtands out a <hi>Storm,</hi> or two, wearies the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and makes him <hi>raiſe</hi> his <hi>Siege.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, conſent not to the <hi>motion;</hi> but ſtill reply in <hi>Negatives.</hi> But, if through <hi>Divine permiſſion,</hi> they prove too ſtrong for you, it's a <hi>Rape,</hi> no <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> — A word unto you of the <hi>more worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> God hath given you the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> you have the <hi>Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> loſe it not for a <hi>Meſs of Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32611:22"/>Let not one <hi>baſe Luſt</hi> deface the <hi>Image</hi> of your <hi>Creatour.</hi> To be <hi>foiled</hi> by your <hi>inferiour</hi> is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable: and for the <hi>Foot</hi> to rule the <hi>Head,</hi> is another <hi>Antipodes,</hi> and no leſs, the <hi>Monſtrous.</hi> Let not her, who was given to thee for an <hi>Help,</hi> be the occaſion of thy fall; leſt thou be like one of thoſe <hi>Simple ones,</hi> a man <hi>void of underſtanding, that goeth as an Ox to to the Slaughter, or as a Fool to the Correction of the Stocks;</hi> Prov. vii. 7, 22. Yet in this thou art onely <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and that's enough too; for <hi>her houſe is the way to Hell, going down to the Chambers of death;</hi> verſe 27. But to <hi>importune, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates</hi> thy fault. And now, thou <hi>man after God's own heart, thou</hi> wert more in the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then <hi>Bath-ſheba,</hi> deeper in the <hi>mire,</hi> then ſhe. Thou wert her <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and ſhouldeſt have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32611:22"/>been rather to her a <hi>Shelter</hi> from the <hi>Storm,</hi> an <hi>Haven</hi> of <hi>repoſe,</hi> and a <hi>refuge</hi> in time of <hi>need.</hi> What's a <hi>Trembling Partridge</hi> in the gripes</hi> of a <hi>towring Falcon?</hi> Sweet God! how ſoon may <hi>we lapſe,</hi> when thy <hi>choiceſt Saints</hi> have <hi>fallen?</hi> If any be <hi>guilty</hi> this way, with <hi>Amnon, hate</hi> the Sin <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times more,</hi> then e're you <hi>loved</hi> it, turn that <hi>Tamar</hi> out, and <hi>barr</hi> the <hi>door</hi> after her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Meditations upon the <hi>Virgin Mary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EVE, thou wert not ſo <hi>bitter</hi> to us, but here's one as <hi>Sweet.</hi> Thou didſt <hi>eat</hi> of a <hi>ſowre Apple,</hi> and <hi>thy childrens Teeth were ſet on edge.</hi> Through thee we all were at <hi>a loſs,</hi> in a winding <hi>maze,</hi> and <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth</hi> of Sorrow, not knowing which way to <hi>get out.</hi> Thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32611:23"/>didſt drive us both from a <hi>Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial</hi> and <hi>Celeſtial Paradiſe.</hi> But <hi>Mary,</hi> like to <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> hath <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run</hi> thee, and brought us <hi>good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> even <hi>of great joy to all people.</hi> She was delivered of a <hi>ſon,</hi> whoſe name is <hi>Jeſus, who ſhall ſave his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their ſins.</hi> O the <hi>height,</hi> and <hi>depth,</hi> the <hi>length,</hi> and <hi>breadth of God his goodneſs towards man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind!</hi> Thoſe, that <hi>ſat in darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>in the Shadow of death,</hi> have ſeen <hi>a marvellous Light.</hi> Now the <hi>ſlaves</hi> are taken from the <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> and all the <hi>Priſoners ſet free.</hi> We are now out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that <hi>Houſe of Bondage,</hi> and <hi>journeying</hi> through a <hi>vaſt Wilderneſs,</hi> to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which <hi>flows with Milk,</hi> and <hi>Hony.</hi> Bleſſed art thou, <hi>fair Maiden,</hi> among <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> for, no ſooner was <hi>the Voyce</hi> ſounded in our <hi>Eart,</hi> but our <hi>Hearts;</hi> leaped in the <hi>womb</hi> of our Bodies for <hi>joy.</hi> Our <hi>year of <hi>Jubile</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:32611:23"/>is come: and not the <hi>Jews</hi> onely, but the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>gladneſs,</hi> and <hi>joy,</hi> and <hi>honour;</hi> yea <hi>joy,</hi> and <hi>gladneſs,</hi> a <hi>Feaſt</hi> and a <hi>good day.</hi> Heſter. viii. 16, 17. But not to <hi>Hyperbolize</hi> too much, leſt I <hi>rob God</hi> of his <hi>honour,</hi> I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſs. Thou wert <hi>greatly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and now a <hi>Glorious Saint</hi> in heaven; for God hath <hi>regarded the lowlineſs of his Hand-maiden,</hi> and, behold! <hi>from hence forth all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall call thee</hi> Bleſſed. <hi>For he, that is Mighty, hath done to thee great things, and Holy is his Name.</hi> Yet we will not free thee from <hi>Original Sin</hi> (as ſome dream) make an <hi>exception,</hi> when the <hi>Rule</hi> is <hi>general</hi> without any. Hadſt thou not born <hi>Chriſt</hi> in thy <hi>heart</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> as well as in thy <hi>Womb,</hi> and brought him forth in a <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied life,</hi> as thou didſt into the <hi>world,</hi> thou hadſt but ſhook</hi> the <hi>Tree, beat</hi> the <hi>Buſh,</hi> or <hi>ſtarted</hi> a <hi>Hare,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:32611:24"/>produced a <hi>Saviour</hi> to thy <hi>Fellows,</hi> and been a <hi>Caſt-away</hi> thy <hi>ſelf.</hi> But thou ſhakeſt off thoſe <hi>Vermine</hi> at once, putteſt to <hi>Non-plus</hi> thy baſe <hi>Paraſites,</hi> and <hi>Clawbacks,</hi> as if they were <hi>Planet-ſtruck. My Soul doth magnifie the Lord, and my Spirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour.</hi> What <hi>Spirit</hi> then was he of, that belched this <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi> Hear it, and let both Ears ringle — Mary <hi>is the Mediatrix of our Salvation, of our Conjunction, Juſtification, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, Interceſſion,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi> How doth this agree with her own <hi>Magnificate?</hi> But why ſhould I foul my hands with ſuch <hi>dirt,</hi> and <hi>rubbiſh?</hi> — Learn <hi>humility</hi> from the <hi>Mother of our Lord;</hi> even from her, who was <hi>highly favoured,</hi> and be not conceited of your own <hi>worthey, ſhe-Saints.</hi> God ſees <hi>no ſin</hi> in you, as you would make us believe, and therefore are <hi>above Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:32611:24"/>The <hi>Preaching of the Word,</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> according to <hi>Divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> concerns you not; for you are <hi>Babes of Grace,</hi> and by your <hi>ſecond Baptiſm,</hi> contrary to <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> your ſins are <hi>waſhed</hi> off. This is the <hi>Tale</hi> you tell us; though, with the <hi>Sow,</hi> that was <hi>waſhed,</hi> you are turned again to your <hi>Wallowing in the Mire;</hi> 2 Pet. ii. 22. Never had the <hi>Devil</hi> ſuch an <hi>Harveſt</hi> ſince the world was, as in theſe <hi>late Times</hi> of <hi>Reformation:</hi> and who would think it? Any with <hi>half aney</hi> might well ſee, what <hi>ſad effects</hi> that thing, called <hi>Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> would produce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Miriam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have met now with a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſs,</hi> and a <hi>Virgin</hi> both; one,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32611:25"/>that was <hi>Siſter</hi> to a <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt.</hi> But this did not ſo much <hi>Enn<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble</hi> her, as her <hi>Vertues;</hi> for her <hi>chiefeſt Ornaments</hi> were the <hi>Graces</hi> of her <hi>Soul,</hi> and the more <hi>precious Jewels</hi> were incloſed in that <hi>Cabinet.</hi> How bravely didſt thou <hi>lead</hi> thy women in their <hi>dance</hi> before the Lord? With what <hi>grace</hi> didſt thou <hi>foot it?</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſtep <hi>ſounded forth</hi> the praiſes of the <hi>moſt High.</hi> Thy <hi>Song</hi> was <hi>gracious,</hi> and, like thy <hi>Spirit,</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns <hi>to him, that gave it.</hi> The <hi>ſubject</hi> of it was <hi>praiſes,</hi> and their <hi>Object</hi> the <hi>Lord.</hi> Like the <hi>Smoak</hi> of <hi>Incenſe,</hi> they aſcend <hi>upwards;</hi> and, as a moſt <hi>ſweet Perfume,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe a redolent <hi>ſmell</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Camp.</hi> Surely, <hi>this was no other, then the houſe of God, and this was the Gate of Heaven.</hi> Hear the <hi>burden</hi> of her <hi>ſong,</hi> and let it <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh</hi> your hearts, and draw them to divine <hi>contemplation.</hi> Notone
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32611:25"/>
                  <hi>ſyllable,</hi> but <hi>Emphatical.</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod. xv. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Sing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, for he hath triumphed gloriouſly: the horſe, and his Rider hath he thrown into the Sea.</hi> — Moſt <hi>Angelical!</hi> when the matter of our <hi>exaltation</hi> intends onely the <hi>glory</hi> of God, when the <hi>ſtream</hi> of our affections run that way. <hi>Incomparable</hi> is that <hi>Harmony,</hi> when every <hi>ſtring</hi> ſpeaks an <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah:</hi> and that voice <hi>Seraphical,</hi> which warbles forth ſuch <hi>Muſical Airs</hi> to the <hi>piercing</hi> of the Clouds. O my Soul how divine are thy <hi>raptures,</hi> into what <hi>extaſie</hi> of joy art thou ſwallowed! Mayſt thou, with <hi>Noah's Dove,</hi> finde no reſt for the <hi>ſole of thy foot,</hi> till thou return to this <hi>Ark.</hi> Let that <hi>Mariner</hi> ſuffer <hi>Shipwrack,</hi> which will not make to this <hi>Port;</hi> and thoſe <hi>Rivers</hi> before ever <hi>dryed up</hi> whoſe <hi>reflux</hi> tends not to that <hi>Sea,</hi> where they have their <hi>flux,</hi> and <hi>overflowings.</hi> — Lift up thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32611:26"/>ſelf then, thou <hi>Worldling,</hi> and let not thy thoughts, with <hi>Staan,</hi> compaſs the Earth <hi>to, and fro,</hi> and walk <hi>up and down</hi> in it. Thou <hi>Dor,</hi> end not thy <hi>flight</hi> ever upon a <hi>dunghill.</hi> Prove not thy ſelf <hi>unnatural.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Os homini ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime dedit, celumquoe tueri Juſsit. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>To man an erect Front, and Face, is given;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That he might Soar aloft, and look t'wards heaven.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seek thoſe things, which are above, where</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſitteth on the right hand of God;</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> he, that was <hi>wrapt</hi> into the <hi>third heaven;</hi> Coloſſ. 3.1. — The <hi>Birds</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> the mute <hi>Fiſhes</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and brute <hi>Beaſts</hi> will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thee. They all move in their <hi>proper Sphere. Philoſophy</hi> will tell thee, that <hi>ponderous</hi> things tend <hi>downward,</hi> and <hi>light</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Throw but a <hi>Stone</hi> in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32611:26"/>
                  <hi>Air,</hi> and how it will haſt to its <hi>proper Center?</hi> Take a <hi>Fiſh</hi> out of the <hi>water,</hi> and it will <hi>gaſp</hi> for Breath. Shall all Creatures both <hi>Senſitive, Vegetative,</hi> the <hi>inſectile</hi> too, the poor ſilly <hi>Fly,</hi> praiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> in their <hi>kind</hi> and is the <hi>Prince</hi> of all, <hi>Man</hi> alone, defective? Shall he <hi>ſo baſely degenerate?</hi> The <hi>Poet</hi> will clear the Point.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Populus me ſibilat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horat.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plaudo ipſe domi, et nummos contemplar in area.—</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The people hiſs at me, they laugh, and at me wink,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At home I praiſe my ſelf, and count my Chink.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>With the blind <hi>Mole,</hi> the wretch is ever <hi>under ground,</hi> and caſting up alwaies <hi>Earth</hi> above him. As a <hi>Pioner</hi> he, and as another <hi>Nero,</hi> he rips the <hi>womb</hi> of his <hi>mother.</hi> Like <hi>green</hi> and <hi>liquid fuel,</hi> he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32611:27"/>
                  <hi>quencheth</hi> that fire, which ſhould <hi>kindle</hi> his thoughts into an <hi>holy Flame,</hi> and make them <hi>Sparkle,</hi> and mount <hi>upward</hi> to heaven. — Though he <hi>liveth, moveth,</hi> and hath his <hi>being</hi> from God onely: yet he will not pay one <hi>Pepper corn</hi> of Thankfullneſs, in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his <hi>Lord,</hi> of whom he holds all, that he injoys, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but <hi>Tenant-at-will,</hi> may every <hi>minute</hi> be ejected, turned out his <hi>benſe of Clay,</hi> and caſt into that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Priſon,</hi> from whence he muſt never expect <hi>Redemption,</hi> till he hath paid the <hi>uttermoſt mite.</hi>—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>Meditations upon</hi> Hannah.</head>
               <p>HEre's a <hi>ſteril</hi> Woman, but not <hi>Barren:</hi> for ſhe is <hi>big</hi> with <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>bare</hi> in her Soul thoſe <hi>lovely Twins</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Supplication.</hi> She was not <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:32611:27"/>with <hi>Rachel; Give me Childen, or elſe I dye:</hi> but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>addreſses</hi> her ſelf to him, who hath the <hi>Key of the womb, and who alone withheld the fruit of it.</hi> She, in the <hi>bitterneſs</hi> of her Soul, prays to the <hi>Lord:</hi> yet her <hi>Lips</hi> move onely, to prevent all <hi>ſiniſter</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions. She was not <hi>long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winded hypocritical Phariſee.</hi> No <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi> or <hi>gifted siſter,</hi> thoſe <hi>pretenders</hi> of <hi>Sanctitie,</hi> who <hi>have a name that they live, but are</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Revel iii. I.</note> 
                  <hi>dead.</hi> Neither was it out of too much <hi>fondneſs,</hi> or <hi>indulgency,</hi> to <hi>dandle a puppet</hi> on her knee, which is the fault of many <hi>mothers,</hi> neglecting, the mean while, the main buſineſs, it's <hi>breeding</hi> and <hi>Religious educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but <hi>vows,</hi> and <hi>performs</hi> it too, to give him unto the Lord <hi>all the days of his life.</hi> I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire her Pietie, and deſervedly ſay of her, as they ſometime of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith; There is not ſuch a Woman
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32611:28"/>in the Earth.</hi> She hath now a <hi>Son,</hi> and ſhe brings him to <hi>Eli,</hi> and the <hi>Child miniſters unto the Lord before the Prieſt.</hi> Our <hi>Women,</hi> for the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> part, run into <hi>extremes,</hi> either they are too <hi>cruel,</hi> or too <hi>mild.</hi> The <hi>mean</hi> in which <hi>virtue</hi> conſiſts, that <hi>arrow</hi> flyeth beyond them. Some are rather <hi>Step-dames,</hi> then <hi>natural Mothers.</hi> Others again, with the <hi>Ape,</hi> kill their <hi>young</hi> with <hi>embracing.</hi> This, of the two, is more Common with the <hi>feminine gender.</hi> Their beloved <hi>Adonijahs</hi> they will not <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> at any hand, or once ſay, <hi>Why have you done ſo;</hi> 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> i. 6. They give them the <hi>Rains,</hi> and care not, though they run to the <hi>Devil. Hawking, Hunting,</hi> and ſo forth, are the <hi>Arms</hi> they bear, that you may know from what houſe they come. Needs muſt that <hi>Garden</hi> be overgrown with <hi>weeds,</hi> when it's no better look'd too. <hi>Nature</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:32611:28"/>without <hi>Art,</hi> or <hi>Science,</hi> is blind. We are not <hi>born</hi> religious, but are made ſo through <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous education.</hi> This makes us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone differ from <hi>Brutes,</hi> and gives the <hi>diſtinction.</hi> Take a <hi>Colt</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken, and who can back him? So, without <hi>diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>goot nurturing</hi> of youth, they become unſerviceable in <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and have no more <hi>Savour</hi> in them, then there is in the <hi>white</hi> of an <hi>egg.</hi> Yet this is the height of many <hi>womens</hi> ambition, if they can but leave their <hi>Brats</hi> a fair <hi>revenue,</hi> to be honoured in the <hi>World,</hi> it's all they look for; let their <hi>Souls</hi> Sink, or Swim, be <hi>Saved,</hi> or <hi>Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> O Salvage <hi>Mothers!</hi> What anſwer will you one day give at <hi>God's Tribunal</hi>-Seat for your neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect? <hi>Your Children ſhall dye in their iniquity: but their blood will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a your hand.</hi> They, whom you ſo dearly loved, or rather
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32611:29"/>hated; will be bound to <hi>Curſe</hi> you, and with horrour break— <hi>Let the day periſh, wherein we were born, and the night, wherein it was ſaid, that a man-Childe is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved!</hi> Why dyed we not from the <hi>Womb?</hi> why did we not give up the Ghoſt, when we came out of the <hi>Belly?</hi> Why did the <hi>knees</hi> prevent us, or why the <hi>breaſts,</hi> that we ſhould ſuck? <hi>Job.</hi> iii. 3, 11, 22. See, ſee to it in time, and be not the mean of their <hi>eternal death,</hi> to whom you once gave a <hi>temporal life.</hi>— But, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, Being young, ſhe devotes him to the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>ſervice. Samuel</hi> miniſters before the Lord, being a Childe girded with a linen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod. Sam.</hi> ii. 18. — She thought no <hi>Maſter</hi> ſo worthy of him, as God, nor any <hi>Service</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to <hi>Divine.</hi> A <hi>Star</hi> ſeems ſmall, and contemptible in the eys of many, though it be <hi>great,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:32611:29"/>and <hi>honourable</hi> in the <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>Acceptions</hi> of the <hi>Almighty.</hi> The <hi>Ministery</hi> is of ſo <hi>mean</hi> Eſteem with ſome, that, with <hi>Jeroboam, they</hi> think the <hi>loweſt of the people</hi> are good enough to <hi>ſerve</hi> that <hi>Turn.</hi> The <hi>yonger Brother</hi> muſt be the <hi>Parſon;</hi> when the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir</hi> looks a ſquint at it, as a thing far <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath</hi> him, a <hi>deſcenſion</hi> too baſe, and <hi>derogative</hi> to his <hi>Birth. Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> eyes water at the <hi>Sun;</hi> and none, but <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s <hi>Dunghill. Cock,</hi> will prefer a <hi>Barly-Corn</hi> before a <hi>Jewel.</hi> But, <hi>Be in known unto all Men by theſe preſents,</hi> whoſoever thou art, and how <hi>high</hi> ſoever thou lookeſt; <hi>Thou</hi> honoureſt not the <hi>Calling,</hi> but the <hi>Calling thee.</hi> What greater Honour, then to be <hi>Fiſhers of m<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n?</hi> To be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental</hi> in the <hi>ſaving</hi> of <hi>one Soul,</hi> and reſcuing it <hi>out of the Power of Sathan,</hi> that <hi>Apollyon,</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> is more <hi>glorious,</hi> then to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:32611:30"/>the <hi>whole World.</hi> I will end with that of King <hi>Charles the Firſt</hi> of <hi>Bleſſed Memory.</hi>—<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>ΕΙ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΙΚΗ,</hi> upon the denying his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> the Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of His Chaplains.</note> 
                  <hi>Indeed, I think, both Offices,</hi> Regal, <hi>and</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal, <hi>might well become the ſame Perſon, as antiently they were under one Name, and the united Rights of Primogeniture. Nor could I follow better</hi> Preſidents, <hi>if I were able; then thoſe two eminent Kings,</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and</hi> Solomon; <hi>Not more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their Crowns, and Scepters, then one was for devout Pſalms, and Prayers; the other for his divine Parables: Whence the one aſſumed the Name of a</hi> Prophet, <hi>and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a</hi> Preacher. <hi>Titles indeed of greater Honour, if rightly placed; then any of thoſe the</hi> Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours <hi>affected, from the Nations they ſubdued: it being infinitely more glorious to convert Souls to God's Church by the World; then to conquer men to a Subjection by the Sword.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:32611:30"/>
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Phinehas.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre's matter both of <hi>Joy,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow.</hi> Tidings came to this <hi>gravid Woman,</hi> and near <hi>Her Time;</hi> that the <hi>Ark of God</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and that her <hi>Husband,</hi> and <hi>Father-in-Law</hi> were dead.— <hi>Heavy, diſconſolate</hi> News, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to diſſolve into <hi>Tears</hi> an heart of <hi>Flint,</hi> to break a <hi>Triangle</hi> of <hi>Stone.</hi> And, indeed, I can ſcarce refrain my Self in the penning ſo <hi>Sad</hi> a <hi>Story.</hi> Her <hi>Soul,</hi> no queſtion, was <hi>vexed</hi> within her, and, with <hi>Rebekah,</hi> in the <hi>Womb</hi> of it She had <hi>much Struggling.</hi> Yet at laſt the <hi>Oil</hi> ſwims at the <hi>Top,</hi> the deepeſt <hi>Wound,</hi> which went nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt her heart, was the <hi>loſs</hi> of the <hi>Ark. The G<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ory is departed from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for the Ark of God is taken;</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> iv. 22. And, this being ſaid, She falls <hi>aſleep</hi> One
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32611:31"/>would have thought the <hi>Birth</hi> of her <hi>Son</hi> might ſomewhat have <hi>aſſwaged</hi> her <hi>Grief,</hi> and, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <hi>Cordial,</hi> in part have <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> or, at leaſt, eas'd the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers</hi> of her Spirit. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will do it, like a <hi>Veſſel ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged,</hi> ſhe <hi>ſink<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and, being full of anguiſh, wanting <hi>Vent,</hi> burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. — Nothing ſhould go ſo nigh a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> touch them more to <hi>the quick,</hi> then the decay of <hi>Religion;</hi> when they ſee <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Service,</hi> and his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> in an <hi>Eclipſe;</hi> or, as this <hi>Good Woman,</hi> the <hi>Ark</hi> even <hi>violently</hi> taken from them, by <hi>rude,</hi> and <hi>uncircumciſed</hi> Hands. I remember that <hi>Paſſage</hi> of <hi>Camelia,</hi> the Mother of the <hi>Gracchi;</hi> when a Matron of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania</hi> came to viſit her, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have a Sight of her <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els;</hi> She, waving it, held her in diſcourſe, until her <hi>Sons</hi> came home: and then, pointing to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32611:31"/>them, ſaid, <hi>Haec ſunt Ornamenta mea; Theſe are my Jewels, my Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments.</hi> Even ſo the pure <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> and the lawful <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments;</hi> which are the <hi>Marks</hi> of a <hi>true Church,</hi> are, at leaſt ſhould be, the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and the only diſtinct <hi>Characters</hi> between the <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>falſe Church.</hi> The <hi>loſs</hi> of theſe ſhould moſt perplex us, as things of <hi>higheſt Concernment;</hi> being <hi>Means</hi> appointed of God to the <hi>eternal Welfare,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of our <hi>Souls.</hi> This ſhould be the proper <hi>Subject</hi> of our <hi>Sorrow.</hi> To ſee <hi>Religion</hi> decay, <hi>Charity</hi> wax <hi>cold,</hi> the <hi>houſe of Prayer</hi> made a <hi>Den of Theeves,</hi> as we have of <hi>late.</hi> To ſee <hi>Profeſſion</hi> a <hi>Cloak</hi> to <hi>palliate</hi> mens <hi>Avarice;</hi> the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> able, and faithful <hi>Paſtours,</hi> removed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Corners, <hi>plundered,</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred,</hi> and many not, as yet, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored;</hi> and to ſee a Company of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32611:32"/>ignorant <hi>Balaamites,</hi> more fit, with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> to divide <hi>Wood,</hi> rather then the <hi>Word,</hi> to pert up, and to <hi>poyſon</hi> the people with <hi>Errours, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> of <hi>Devils,</hi> to the danger of many thouſand <hi>Souls.</hi> This, I ſay, ſhould ſtrike a <hi>ſudden Damp</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, put us into a <hi>Cold Sweat,</hi> and make us <hi>weep</hi> into a <hi>Torrent;</hi> for <hi>the Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the Ark of God is taken.</hi> If this will not cauſe their <hi>Tears;</hi> I pray <hi>God</hi> they be not one day caſt into <hi>utter Darkneſs,</hi> where there is <hi>weeping, wailing, and gnaſhing of Teeth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>pleaſant wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> is at a <hi>Period,</hi> and the <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>deep Winter</hi> approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The ways now are <hi>dirty,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:32611:32"/>no walking <hi>abroad;</hi> onely let us <hi>look out,</hi> and ſee how <hi>foul</hi> the <hi>road</hi> is, in compariſon of what it was. Here is one of <hi>Nilus</hi> Breed, a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Crocodile,</hi> one, whoſe <hi>Tears,</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> were not onely <hi>feigned,</hi> but <hi>miſchievous.</hi> See how <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,</hi> and ſhameleſly ſhe courts him. <hi>And ſhe ſaid, Ly with me;</hi> Gen. xxxix. 7. By this <hi>Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> voice, like another <hi>Herricano,</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thought to blow up the <hi>chaſt youth</hi> with a <hi>Guſt,</hi> and frame him to her Will. The <hi>firſt Onſet</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>repulſe,</hi> ſhe thought to <hi>weary</hi> him through <hi>importunity,</hi> wherefore ſhe ſolicits him <hi>day by day</hi> to <hi>condeſcend;</hi> Verſe 10. but the <hi>powder</hi> will not <hi>take,</hi> and therefore ſhe goes another way to work, and trie, if <hi>opportunity</hi> will do it. But, <hi>alone</hi> together, and <hi>none of the men within, ſhe caught him by his garment, ſaying, Ly with me;</hi> Verſe 12. Yet, for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32611:33"/>all this <hi>Fire,</hi> the <hi>Tinder</hi> will not <hi>burn, Joſeph</hi> is <hi>impregnable,</hi> and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>armour</hi> of <hi>Proof,</hi> no <hi>bullet</hi> can pierce him. Now hear, and wonder, when all her <hi>ſtrings break,</hi> ſhe cries <hi>Whore</hi> firſt, and baſely pretends a <hi>Rope</hi> offered her. <hi>The</hi> Hebrew <hi>Servant, which thou haſt brought unto us, came in unto me to mock me;</hi> Verſe 17. O the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of an <hi>imperious, whoriſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man!</hi> Who would think ſo <hi>fair a face</hi> had ſo <hi>foul an heart!</hi> A <hi>Box</hi> ſo externally <hi>pol ſhed</hi> ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with ſuch <hi>venom?</hi> But no marvel, for a <hi>graceleſs woman</hi> to outvy a <hi>Serpent.</hi> — The <hi>Whore</hi> now is <hi>Carted,</hi> let every <hi>bed und filed</hi> throw <hi>dirt</hi> upon her; for ſhe is hatefull to <hi>God,</hi> a bane to <hi>Youth,</hi> injurious to her <hi>husband,</hi> and a ſhame to her <hi>Sex.</hi> — And you, <hi>Young ones,</hi> in your <hi>ſpring,</hi> and <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wer,</hi> look upon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the world's <hi>mirrour,</hi> the <hi>Chaſt,</hi> the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32611:33"/>
                  <hi>Vertuous.</hi> Can you <hi>view</hi> this piece, and not be <hi>in love</hi> with it? Can you <hi>read</hi> this, and <hi>give your ſtrength to wowen?</hi> Yield not to a <hi>Common Proſtitute.</hi> When this <hi>Syren</hi> ſings, ſtop your <hi>ears,</hi> you run elſe on a <hi>Rock,</hi> or <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</hi> Let your <hi>part</hi> upon the <hi>Stage</hi> of this <hi>would</hi> be <hi>Chaſtitie;</hi> that you may go off with a <hi>Plaudite.</hi> Keep your <hi>virginity</hi> untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo ſhall you be <hi>fit Temples for the Holy Ghoſt. Chriſt</hi> was lay'd in a <hi>new Tomb;</hi> if you would have his Company, let your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> be <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>chaſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Delilah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre is another of the <hi>ſame Form,</hi> an excellent <hi>proficient</hi> in the <hi>Black-Art;</hi> one, that <hi>Coun'd</hi> her <hi>Leſſon</hi> perfectly. She was prettily ſeen in <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> for ſhe could <hi>ſpeak well:</hi> and a <hi>Logician</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:32611:34"/>too, being expert in <hi>Fallacies.</hi> She <hi>proſtitutes,</hi> and gives <hi>Sampſon</hi> her <hi>Body:</hi> but not her <hi>heart;</hi> though ſhe gained <hi>his</hi> to his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Sampſon</hi> was a <hi>Nazarite</hi> from his <hi>Youth,</hi> a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an <hi>Enemy,</hi> to the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer</hi> of their Country by <hi>divine appointment.</hi> The <hi>Lords</hi> plough with his <hi>heifer,</hi> and promiſe to give her, each of them, <hi>eleven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pieces of ſilver,</hi> to get out of him where his <hi>great ſtrength</hi> lay. See how cunningly ſhe carries it: the <hi>Gipſey</hi> hath <hi>Hony</hi> in her <hi>mouth,</hi> but <hi>Gall</hi> in her <hi>heart. Tell me, I pray thee, where thy great Strength lyeth;</hi> and ſo, by her <hi>importunity,</hi> urging him from time to time, that his <hi>Soul was vexed unto death,</hi> he tells her all his <hi>heart;</hi> and he, that with the Jaw-bone of an <hi>Aſs</hi> ſlew a thouſand men, ſhe makes an <hi>Aſs</hi> of him, puts <hi>out</hi> his <hi>Eyes,</hi> and now he <hi>grinds</hi> in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32611:34"/>
                  <hi>Mill,</hi> and is become a <hi>Fool</hi> to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>acircumciſed.</hi> O the <hi>mazie,</hi> and falſe <hi>heart</hi> of an <hi>ungracious Woman!</hi> No <hi>Toad</hi> more replete with <hi>poyſon,</hi> then ſuch an <hi>unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Creature.</hi> A <hi>Vitious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> cancels the bonds of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi> A pure <hi>Maremaid Monſter,</hi> half <hi>woman,</hi> half <hi>fiſh;</hi> or rather an <hi>incarnate Devil:</hi> to betray a confiding <hi>Lover</hi> into the hands of implacable <hi>enemies:</hi> That of the <hi>Poët</hi> with me is <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical; Believe not ſuch a woman, though ſhe ſhould breath her laſt.</hi> What act ſo <hi>horrid,</hi> that a <hi>Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Strumpet</hi> will not do? All former <hi>Familiaritie,</hi> amorous <hi>dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance,</hi> and mutual <hi>embracings,</hi> are all buried in <hi>Oblivion.</hi> Who would truſt a <hi>Whore;</hi> for, <hi>greaſe</hi> her in the <hi>fiſt,</hi> and, if ſhe can, ſhee'l damn thee. All the <hi>Plagues</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> are <hi>bleſſings</hi> to this <hi>Cannibal.</hi> If thou feareſt <hi>God,</hi> tendereſt the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32611:35"/>
                  <hi>Peace</hi> of thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> and mind'ſt the <hi>Salvation</hi> of thy pretious <hi>Soul;</hi> fly the ſight of this <hi>Baſilisk.</hi>— For <hi>Riddles,</hi> ſhe is a <hi>Lamia;</hi> for <hi>enchantments,</hi> a <hi>Circe;</hi> for <hi>Cruelty,</hi> a <hi>Devil.</hi> She is ſo <hi>ugly,</hi> that no <hi>Pen</hi> can draw her <hi>to the Life.</hi> She is a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> which no <hi>Line</hi> can <hi>ſound,</hi> and a <hi>Remora,</hi> that puts a ſtop to <hi>Vertue</hi> in all <hi>Veſſels,</hi> that ſail by her. <hi>Sampſon,</hi> of a <hi>thouſand Tun</hi> Burthen, was ſtay'd by it, and ſo hailed a ſhore by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed,</hi> and then <hi>rifled.</hi> What ſhould I ſay of this <hi>Witch?</hi> Mount <hi>Aetna</hi> ſpits not forth more <hi>Fire,</hi> and her <hi>Smoak</hi> aſcends from the <hi>bottomleſs Pitt.</hi> The wiſh of <hi>Velerius Maximus</hi> to his <hi>friend</hi> ſhall be mine to every <hi>individual; Det Deus omnipotens, ut omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti faemina ſemper libereris: The Omnipotent God deliver thee from an Omnipotent woman.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:32611:35"/>
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Jezebel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom <hi>Evil</hi> to <hi>worſe.</hi> Here have I met with a <hi>pretious Saint.</hi> One, whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> was a <hi>Cloak</hi> to cover her <hi>Villany,</hi> a <hi>Sheep</hi> in ſhew, a <hi>Fox</hi> indeed, a <hi>Wolf</hi> in Cruelty. Theſe three may be compar'd to the three <hi>Furies; Alecto, Megaera,</hi> and <hi>Tiſyphone:</hi> but, of all the Degrees, this is <hi>Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and falls <hi>ſhort</hi> of none, but the <hi>Devil,</hi> which may ſeem a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox</hi> too. It were hard to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a <hi>Play</hi> of her, the <hi>Scene</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Hell,</hi> and the <hi>Stage</hi> ſo <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical,</hi> enough to fright the <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</hi> But ſee an <hi>Act,</hi> or two, and then diſcede the <hi>Houſe</hi> with an <hi>Hiſs. Ahab,</hi> being denyed <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi>'s Vineyard, more ſick in <hi>Mind,</hi> then <hi>Body,</hi> throws him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on the <hi>Bed,</hi> where, like the <hi>troubled Sea,</hi> the <hi>Waters</hi> caſt up
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32611:36"/>
                  <hi>mire,</hi> and <hi>dirt. There's no Peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi> In this Diſtraction comes up the <hi>Monnte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank,</hi> who, to recover him, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies <hi>Poyſon,</hi> making the <hi>Cure</hi> worſe then the <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi> A <hi>dear Purchaſe!</hi> when a man exchangeth his <hi>Soul</hi> for a <hi>Vineyard.</hi> But ſee the <hi>Deviliſhneſs</hi> of this <hi>Woman.</hi> She <hi>writes Letters in</hi> Ahab<hi>'s name, and ſeals them with his Seal,</hi> and ſends them to the <hi>Elders,</hi> and <hi>Nobles.</hi> Mark the <hi>Contents. Proclaim a Faſt, and ſet</hi> Naboth <hi>on high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, and ſet two Sons of</hi> Belial <hi>before him, to bear witneſs againſt him, ſaying, Thou didſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God, and the King; and then carry him out, and ſtone him, that he may dye.</hi> 1 Kings. xxi. 9, 10. O <hi>incomparable villany! impietie</hi> in the <hi>abſtract!</hi> A <hi>Woman?</hi> a <hi>Devil</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Muſt Religion be a <hi>Bawd</hi> to <hi>Murther?</hi> It muſt: but it <hi>aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates</hi> the <hi>Sin,</hi> and contracts <hi>more
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32611:36"/>guilt</hi> to the <hi>Soul. Feigned Sanctitie</hi> is a <hi>double iniquitie,</hi> and they <hi>ſin twice,</hi> who do it under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of <hi>Holineſs.</hi>— This hath ever been the <hi>Common-road</hi> to all <hi>horrid,</hi> and <hi>black</hi> deeds. When we had <hi>no King in</hi> Iſrael, and <hi>every man did as ſeemed beſt in his own eyes; Religion</hi> brought up the <hi>rear,</hi> and the <hi>Scattered Troops</hi> of <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> rallied, and fought under that <hi>Banner.</hi> Should the <hi>Devil</hi> appear dreadfull, he would ſcare the <hi>Witch</hi> her ſelf.— Our pretended <hi>Triennial,</hi> and <hi>long-winded Parliament</hi> (who made this Kingdom another <hi>Ach<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldamae</hi> a <hi>Field of Blood,</hi> and <hi>place of dead men's Sculls.</hi>) put this <hi>vizard</hi> on. <hi>Reformation,</hi> the glorious name of <hi>Reformation</hi> was all the <hi>Cry.</hi> When we were made worſe, then <hi>Gally ſlaves</hi> among the <hi>Turks,</hi> or God's people in <hi>Egypt,</hi> who made <hi>Brick without Straw,</hi> and through
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32611:37"/>intolerable <hi>burdens,</hi> and <hi>impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> even weary of our lives: yet the <hi>Libertie of the Subject,</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> was pretended. But <hi>God,</hi> pitying our miſeries, looked through the <hi>pillar of Fire,</hi> and of the <hi>Cloud,</hi> on the <hi>Hoſt</hi> of theſe <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and troubled them, he took off their <hi>Chariot-wheels,</hi> that they drave <hi>heavily,</hi> and the <hi>Rump</hi> (though not <hi>drowned</hi>) was <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed</hi> in the <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is not a <hi>Sectary,</hi> but hath <hi>Religion</hi> for his pretenſe. <hi>Religion</hi> hat been the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewer,</hi> through which all <hi>Kenels</hi> have run; and, like the <hi>Phyſicians Catholicon,</hi> applyed to all <hi>foul diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</hi> But a <hi>ſeeming Saint</hi> is a <hi>real Devil.</hi> Now to our <hi>Theme</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. She was the firſt <hi>painted woman</hi> we read of, not, like the <hi>Picts,</hi> to <hi>terrifie,</hi> but to <hi>attract.</hi> Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Jehu</hi> came to <hi>Jezreel.</hi> Jeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel <hi>paints her face, and tires her
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32611:37"/>head, and looks out at a window;</hi> 2 King. ix. 30. By this ſhe thought to <hi>captivate</hi> him, before whom <hi>two Kings</hi> could not ſtand. Her firſt <hi>Complement</hi> was,—<hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace, who ſlew his Maſter?</hi> As if ſhe had been no <hi>Homicide,</hi> though ſhe murdered <hi>Naboth.</hi> O the <hi>Deadneſs</hi> of a <hi>cauteriſed Soul!</hi> Coul'd ſhe ſpeak this, and yet guilty of <hi>innocent Blood?</hi> Truly, <hi>Cuſtom</hi> in <hi>Sin</hi> takes from us all <hi>ſince,</hi> and feeling of it. No <hi>judgment</hi> ſo <hi>fearfull,</hi> as a <hi>benummed Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> when one perpetrates a <hi>ſin,</hi> and never <hi>mindes</hi> it. The <hi>Sea,</hi> that's now <hi>calm,</hi> when a <hi>ſtorm</hi> comes, will prove <hi>turbulent,</hi> and cauſe it to rage, and foam. <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> which are ſtopped, when the <hi>Banks</hi> give way, break in with <hi>more violence.</hi> At one time, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou wilt ſay to thy <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> as <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Elijah, Haſt thou found me out, O mine enemy, haſt thou
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32611:38"/>found me? Tuta eſſe ſcelera, ſecura non poſſunt.</hi> Thy ſins may, to thy thinking, be <hi>ſafe;</hi> but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>ſecure.</hi> Thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> will <hi>bark,</hi> and <hi>bite,</hi> and without <hi>Repentance,</hi> that <hi>worm</hi> live to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie.</hi> Lake <hi>Prometheus</hi> his <hi>Vulture,</hi> it will continually gnaw thy <hi>heart,</hi> and add to the meaſure of thy endleſs <hi>torments.</hi> She <hi>paints</hi> her <hi>Face,</hi> and <hi>paints</hi> her <hi>Sin,</hi> which nothing can waſh off but <hi>Tears</hi> of <hi>contrition</hi> in the blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>— But hath ſhe no <hi>Siſters</hi> living? Yes, and ſuch, who are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> too, which make their <hi>ſins</hi> out of meaſure ſinfull. We have many <hi>Jezebels,</hi> who, when <hi>natural Beautie</hi> falls ſhort, they would repair by <hi>art.</hi> Angli <hi>quaſi Angeli,</hi> ſaid a <hi>Pope</hi> once of ſome of our <hi>Boys,</hi> who were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; but, ſhould be have ſeen ſome of our <hi>Women,</hi> he would have changed his <hi>Tale;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32611:38"/>of <hi>Angels,</hi> have given them the deſerved <hi>Epithete</hi> of <hi>incarnate Devils.</hi> Many ſo <hi>dawb,</hi> and <hi>ſlaver</hi> their <hi>faces,</hi> that they look more like <hi>Puppets,</hi> then <hi>women;</hi> and <hi>pictures</hi> rather, then <hi>living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> As for <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Holineſs,</hi> that ſhew of <hi>Godlineſs, denying the power,</hi> not ſuch an <hi>harveſt</hi> ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> as in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended times of <hi>Reformation.</hi> Well, mark the <hi>reſult, Jezebel</hi> was devoured by <hi>Dogs.</hi> Repent, you <hi>degenerate women,</hi> that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not a <hi>prey</hi> to the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Athaliah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Way,</hi> as yet I ſee, is <hi>very foul.</hi> I thought the <hi>laſt</hi> would admit <hi>no Compariſon;</hi> but I have now met with her <hi>Match.</hi> They may very well go for <hi>Siſters:</hi> for they are as <hi>like,</hi> as two <hi>Twins,</hi> bloody <hi>Nimrods</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:32611:39"/>both, and <hi>mighty Hunters before the Lord.</hi> I may ſay of this as is Recorded of <hi>Caligula,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Lutum Sanguine maceratum. <hi>Suet.</hi>
                  </note> a <hi>Lump of clay ſoaked in Blood.</hi> Her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> was altogether <hi>ſanguine:</hi> and no <hi>water</hi> could quench her <hi>Thirſt,</hi> but choice <hi>Spirits of Life;</hi> for She deſtroys <hi>all</hi> the<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Kin. xi. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Seed Royal. Ambition</hi> is the <hi>Cut-throat</hi> of neareſt <hi>Relations:</hi> and, where it <hi>reigns,</hi> there's no room for <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</hi> Like <hi>Hell,</hi> and the <hi>Grave,</hi> it's <hi>never ſatisfied.</hi> If a <hi>Crown</hi> be the <hi>Gain,</hi> all the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unds</hi> are let looſe. <hi>How many</hi> have broke their <hi>Necks</hi> in the purſuit of it? Nay; <hi>how many</hi> have damned their <hi>Soul,</hi> to Climb up this <hi>Culmen?</hi> It is ſo ſweet a <hi>Bait,</hi> that many <hi>Gud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons</hi> have nibbled ſo long at it; that they have been <hi>caught</hi> to their Deſtruction. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> were great <hi>Gameſters</hi> at it: One could brook no <hi>Superiour,</hi> the other ſcorned a <hi>Competitiour;</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:32611:39"/>but their <hi>Exit</hi> was miſerable, and their <hi>Sun</hi> went <hi>down in Blood. Great Alexander,</hi> who grieved he had not <hi>more Worlds</hi> to Conquer, was <hi>nipped</hi> in the <hi>Eud,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within a <hi>winding-Sheet,</hi> and a <hi>Coffin. Bajazet,</hi> the <hi>Turk,</hi> whom once all <hi>Aſia</hi> could not hold, was at laſt <hi>cooped</hi> up in a <hi>Cage;</hi> where he might complain to his <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> and dolefully <hi>Tune forth</hi> his Misfortunes. <hi>Crook'd-Back Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> the <hi>Vſurper,</hi> (who, to gain a <hi>Crown,</hi> murdered his <hi>Nephews</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and drowned his own <hi>Natural Brother,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> in a <hi>But</hi> of <hi>Malmſey</hi>) after <hi>three</hi> Years, and odd Moneths Reign, had his full <hi>Compenſation,</hi> and <hi>Retribution:</hi> For he was ſlain in <hi>Boſworth field,</hi> and, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeared with <hi>dirt,</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> was tyed behind a <hi>Purſivant,</hi> to the <hi>Scoff,</hi> and <hi>Wonder</hi> of both <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> But, what need I ſearch
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32611:40"/>the <hi>Records,</hi> or look back to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity?</hi> 'Tis <hi>freſh</hi> in <hi>our</hi> Memories; <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi> not long ſince was <hi>terrible,</hi> as <hi>Captain Drake</hi>'s was to the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> What <hi>Seas</hi> of <hi>Blood</hi> did he <hi>wade through?</hi> What <hi>Numbers</hi> of <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Children,</hi> and <hi>Widows,</hi> did he make, whoſe <hi>Cryes,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> would have forced a <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy</hi> from an hard-hearted <hi>Jew,</hi> to <hi>condole</hi> with them? Into what <hi>Miſeries</hi> were the <hi>Royal Party,</hi> thoſe <hi>noble Souls,</hi> who fought for <hi>God,</hi> and their <hi>King,</hi> plunged? <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> would then have made any <hi>miſerable.</hi> King <hi>Saul</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Sam. xv. 9.</note> ſaved <hi>alive</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> of the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and of the <hi>Oxen,</hi> and of the <hi>Fatlings,</hi> and of the <hi>Lambs;</hi> but every thing, that was <hi>vile,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe,</hi> he <hi>utterly deſtroyed.</hi> But here, on the <hi>contrary,</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> of men, and the <hi>fatteſt, harmleſs</hi> as <hi>Sheep,</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> as <hi>Lambs,</hi> the <hi>nobly-born,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32611:40"/>true-hearted Gentry,</hi> and the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Clergy,</hi> were hailed to the Slaughter; and the <hi>vile, refuſe,</hi> and <hi>raſcal People,</hi> the <hi>rebellious,</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmatical</hi> were reſerved. <hi>Ambition,</hi> onely <hi>Ambition,</hi> was the <hi>Devil,</hi> that let looſe that <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Blood-Hound.</hi> But, mark his ſad <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi>— His <hi>Vale</hi> to the world was unhappy: for He<note n="(d)" place="margin">Intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit ut Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit ut Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus est ut Canis. <hi>Dictum de</hi> Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio Octavo <hi>Papa.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>came</hi> in like a <hi>Fox,</hi> He <hi>reigned</hi> as a <hi>Wolf,</hi> and <hi>dyed</hi> like a <hi>Dog.</hi> And, behold this <hi>miſcreant</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Hell</hi>'s <hi>fourth Fury,</hi> after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, being <hi>put forth</hi> the <hi>Ranges,</hi> is ſlain; 2 <hi>King.</hi> xi. 16. <hi>Sic tranſit gloria Mundi.</hi> Thus the <hi>ſeeming Glory</hi> of the world <hi>viniſheth.</hi> And the <hi>Bladder,</hi> blow up with Wind, with one <hi>Spurn</hi> is gone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:32611:41"/>
               <head>Meditations upon <hi>Sapphira,</hi> Acts v.</head>
               <p>WE ſay, <hi>The nigher the church, the farther from God;</hi> and, indeed, many times it proves ſo, take it either by way of <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> or <hi>Station,</hi> and the <hi>Proverb</hi> will often be made good. A <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> is <hi>ſold,</hi> but a <hi>part</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is brought, and layed at the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Feet.</hi> 'Tis <hi>impious,</hi> and <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> to part <hi>Man,</hi> and <hi>Wife;</hi> for <hi>thoſe, whom God hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let no man put aſunder.</hi> But, it had been happy for <hi>Sapphira,</hi> ſhe had been leſs <hi>indulgent,</hi> and <hi>diſtinct</hi> in this particular. Well; ſhe was <hi>privy</hi> to the <hi>Sale,</hi> and to the <hi>Sin. Grace</hi> is <hi>Communicative;</hi> and ſo is <hi>Vice.</hi> A <hi>drowning Man</hi> plucks the <hi>next,</hi> that's to him, in with him; and one, ſtruck with the <hi>Plague,</hi> loves <hi>Company.</hi> When <hi>Sin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32611:41"/>the <hi>Sign</hi> is in <hi>Gemini,</hi> and brings forth <hi>Twins. Sacril<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge</hi> walks not <hi>alone;</hi> but muſt have a <hi>lye</hi> to <hi>wait</hi> upon it. <hi>Yea; for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,</hi> ſaid this <hi>Poor Soul:</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>falls down at the Apoſtles feet, and yields up the Ghoſt;</hi> Verſe 10.<note n="(a)" place="margin">ubi pecata, ibi procella. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> A <hi>Storm</hi> is ever at the heels of <hi>Impietie:</hi> and, where <hi>Sin is Miſtreſs, Sighs</hi> attend as <hi>Hand-maidens.</hi> As <hi>Solomon,</hi> in the <hi>Singnlar Number,</hi> addreſſes his <hi>Speech</hi> to his <hi>Young man,</hi> I will deliver in the <hi>Plural.</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eccles. xi. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Rejoyce, O ye Sinners, and let your hearts chear you, and walk in the waies of your hearts, and in the Sight of your eyes; but know ye, that for all theſe things God will bring you into Judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> with us, as <hi>Fornication</hi> with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> is counted <hi>venial;</hi> though, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in God's eye, <hi>damnable.</hi> If not <hi>ſo; what mean the bleating of the Sheep, and the lowing of the Oxen,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32611:42"/>which I hear?</hi> (as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Soul,</hi> in <hi>another</hi> ſence <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Sam. XV. 14.</note>) Why are <hi>Livings</hi> every where ſo <hi>small,</hi> and, with <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s <hi>Kine,</hi> ſo <hi>lean,</hi> and <hi>il<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-favoured,</hi> that the <hi>Man of God</hi> is fain to <hi>graw</hi> upon a <hi>Cruſt?</hi> Is not this to make <hi>Brick</hi> without <hi>ſtraw?</hi> And yet, which is <hi>beaſtly,</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> they will <hi>exact</hi> the <hi>tale</hi> of their <hi>Bricks,</hi> expect from their <hi>Miniſter</hi> that, which he is not able to <hi>perform.</hi> How can the <hi>Ox</hi> tread out the <hi>Corn,</hi> when his <hi>mouth</hi> is <hi>muzzled?</hi> And how can he <hi>preach,</hi> who hath not <hi>bread</hi> many times to ſatisfy the <hi>hungry bellies</hi> of himſelf, and <hi>Family?</hi> O <hi>Cruelty</hi> to be abhorred! <hi>Aves pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeunt, ferae par<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt, homines ſaeviunt:</hi> the <hi>Birds feed</hi> us, for <hi>Elijah</hi> was fed by <hi>Rvens;</hi> Salvage <hi>Beaſts ſpare</hi> us, ſo the fierce <hi>Lyons Daniel</hi> in the <hi>Den;</hi> but (ſhall I ſpeak it?) <hi>Men</hi> onely are <hi>cruel,</hi> and <hi>devour.</hi> This is that, which brings both <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:32611:42"/>and <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> in <hi>Contempt,</hi> to the <hi>ſcorn</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>ſhame</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and, without repentance, the <hi>damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their <hi>Souls.</hi> For the <hi>affront,</hi> offered to <hi>them,</hi> is offered to <hi>God</hi> himſelf: and 'tis <hi>a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> We know who ſaid it.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luke x. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>He, that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me; and he, that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him, that ſent me.</hi> This <hi>ſimple Woman</hi> came to a <hi>ſudden end</hi> for keeping <hi>Back</hi> part of that, which was her <hi>own,</hi> or perhaps for <hi>concealing</hi> it onely; what <hi>judgement</hi> then muſt they expect, who keep <hi>back,</hi> and <hi>detain</hi> from their <hi>Paſtours</hi> that, which is <hi>their own?</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. xlix. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their ſecret; unto their Aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united.</hi> The <hi>pitifull Phariſee,</hi> who was <hi>an Hypocrite,</hi> a <hi>verbal</hi> onely, and <hi>external Profeſſour,</hi> ſhall one day riſe in <hi>judgment</hi> againſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32611:43"/>
                  <hi>this generation,</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> it; for he paid his <hi>Tithes</hi> even unto <hi>Mint, Anice-ſeed,</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> when ſome <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo called <hi>Nomine, non re,</hi> in <hi>name</hi> onely, would not <hi>willingly</hi> ſpare the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of their Nails. Well; let them <hi>coſen,</hi> and <hi>cheat: Aurum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent</hi> Toloſanum, <hi>they,</hi> or their <hi>poſteritie,</hi> will be met with; and, when the hand of the <hi>Almighty</hi> lights heavie upon them, they will then <hi>cry out,</hi> as the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> did, when the <hi>Ark</hi> was brought into the <hi>Camp; Vae nobis! Vae nobis! Wo be unto us! Wo be unto us!</hi> Hear, and tremble; for the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken it.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mal. iii. 8, 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee. In Tithes, and Offerings. Ye are curſed with a Curſe; for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation,</hi> &amp;c.— Her <hi>next ſin</hi> was <hi>Lying. Yea,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>for ſo much.</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:32611:43"/>Had ſhe left this <hi>out,</hi> and ſpoken <hi>Truth:</hi> her <hi>fault</hi> had been the <hi>leſs,</hi> but now it's <hi>aggravated.</hi> To <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate</hi> a Sin, is bad enough; but to <hi>maintain</hi> it, is a great deal worſe. O <hi>Sapphira!</hi> would thy <hi>Lying</hi> had periſhed with thee; but, <hi>thou</hi> art dead, thy Sin <hi>ſurvives,</hi> and, like a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> hath dilated it ſelf <hi>far</hi> and <hi>wide,</hi> as if from thee <hi>heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> This is thought ſmall; for it is <hi>Epidemical:</hi> yet, it bids <hi>defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and ſpits in the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>Almighty. I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life;</hi> ſaid once thy <hi>Saviour.</hi> What therefore can be more <hi>contrary,</hi> and <hi>oppoſite</hi> to him; then <hi>Falſhood? Every like delights. and rejoyceth in its like;</hi> ſaith <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy.</hi> Now, <hi>thy God</hi> is <hi>Truth,</hi> yea <hi>Truth it ſelf;</hi> by <hi>Conſequent</hi> then <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>Lying</hi> muſt needs be <hi>odible</hi> to him. What <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molument</hi> comes by <hi>Lying?</hi> All, that I know, is onely this, <hi>Shame,</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:32611:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>not to be credited,</hi> when they ſpeak the <hi>Truth.</hi> Let them <hi>weep;</hi> and preſently we ſay, <hi>Crocodili Lacrymae,</hi> Behold the <hi>Tears</hi> of a <hi>Crocodile!</hi> and, let their Speech ſeem never ſo <hi>fair,</hi> and <hi>ſeconded</hi> by <hi>deep Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Imprecations;</hi> Yet, it is but taken as <hi>ridiculous,</hi> and as a <hi>Syren</hi>'s <hi>Song,</hi> that tends onely to the <hi>Ruin</hi> of the poor <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner.</hi> The <hi>female Sex</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the <hi>fairer,</hi> and of a more <hi>tender Conſtitution;</hi> therefore more <hi>attractive:</hi> Yet nothing doth more <hi>imbelliſh</hi> them, then <hi>Vertue,</hi> an <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>harmleſs</hi> Converſation. Their <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> ſhould be ever <hi>Covi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aetours,</hi> and <hi>fellow-Travellers,</hi> and nothing ſhould put a <hi>Divorce</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. The <hi>Calves of our Lips</hi> is <hi>a Sacrifice pleaſing to God;</hi> but it muſt be <hi>without Blemiſh.</hi> He cannot away with <hi>Halting,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accept that, which wants an
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32611:44"/>
                  <hi>Eye.</hi> Me thinks, that <hi>Proverb</hi> ſhould not be amongſt <hi>Chriſtians; Plain dealing is a jewel, and he, that uſeth it, dyes a Beggar.</hi> How! a <hi>Beggar?</hi> this is no <hi>fair play,</hi> and thoſe <hi>ſcales</hi> were not <hi>right,</hi> to waigh <hi>down</hi> ſo <hi>precious</hi> a Commoditie. We have another <hi>equivalent,</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas odium parit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Flattery gets friends, Truth hatred:</hi> but more is the pity. <hi>Tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>publiſh it not in the Streets of</hi> Askelon; leſt <hi>the Daughters of the</hi> Philiſtines <hi>rejoyce, leſt the Daughters of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</hi> Admire the <hi>depth</hi> of this <hi>ſin.</hi> It's a <hi>precipice</hi> ſo <hi>ſteep,</hi> that it will ſtrike terrour in any but to <hi>look down;</hi> and, being once known, by the <hi>grace</hi> of God, deterr all <hi>Paſſengers</hi> from coming <hi>that way. You are of your Father the Devil, and the works of your Father you will do,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He was a murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, and abode not in the truth; becauſe there is no truth in him.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32611:45"/>When he ſpeaketh a lv, he ſpeaketh of his own; for he is a lyer, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it.</hi> John viii. 44. See who brings up the <hi>rear</hi> of the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard.</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Revel. xxi. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>But the Fearfull, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving, and the Abominable, and Murtherers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Lyers, ſhall have their part in the Lake, which burneth with Fire, and Brimſtone; which is the ſecond death.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:32611:45"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
